<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A comfortable corroborative cordial: or, A sovereign antidote against, and preservative from, the horrours &amp; harms of death affording a direction how to live and die, so as to be fortified and fenced against the greatest fears and sharpest sense of that king of terrours. Represented in some observations made upon Rev. 14. 13. Upon occasion of the late death and burial of Mrs. Rebeccah Jackler late wife of Mr. John Jackler of Kings-Lynn in Norfolk, woollen-draper; who deceased Octob. 5. and was buried Octob. 7. 1671. By John Horne, sometime preacher of Gods word in Lynn-Alhallows in the same town. Useful to be considered by all men living in this state of mortality: because there is no man living but must certainly die.</title>
            <author>Horn, John, 1614-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830473</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34925</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34925)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2091:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A comfortable corroborative cordial: or, A sovereign antidote against, and preservative from, the horrours &amp; harms of death affording a direction how to live and die, so as to be fortified and fenced against the greatest fears and sharpest sense of that king of terrours. Represented in some observations made upon Rev. 14. 13. Upon occasion of the late death and burial of Mrs. Rebeccah Jackler late wife of Mr. John Jackler of Kings-Lynn in Norfolk, woollen-draper; who deceased Octob. 5. and was buried Octob. 7. 1671. By John Horne, sometime preacher of Gods word in Lynn-Alhallows in the same town. Useful to be considered by all men living in this state of mortality: because there is no man living but must certainly die.</title>
                  <author>Horn, John, 1614-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 117, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Radcliffe, and N. Thompson, for B. Southwood at the Star next to Serjeants-Inn in Chancery-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epitaphium in amicam suam Dam. Rebeccam Jackler" is on final leaf in Latin (H8r) and in English (H8v) as, "An epitaph upon his deceased friend Mrs. R. J.".</note>
                  <note>Copy stained and tightly bound with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIV, 13 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Comfortable Corroborative Cordial: OR, A Sovereign Antidote againſt, And Preſervative from, the Horrours &amp; Harms of <hi>DEATH:</hi> Affording a Direction how to Live and Die, ſo as to be fortified and fenced againſt the greareſt fears and ſharpeſt ſenſe of that KING of <hi>TERROURS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Repreſented in ſome Obſervations made upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. Upon occaſion of the late Death and Burial of Mrs. <hi>REBECCAH JACKLER</hi> Late Wife of Mr. <hi>John Jackler</hi> of <hi>Kings-Lynn</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Woollen-Draper; who deceaſed <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. and was buried <hi>Octob.</hi> 7. 1671.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Horn,</hi> Sometime Preacher of Gods Word in <hi>Lynn-Alhallows</hi> in the ſame Town.</p>
            <p>Uſeful to be conſidered by all men living in this ſtate of Mortality: Becauſe there is no man living but muſt certainly Die.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let me die the death of the righteous: and let my laſt end be like to his.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Numb. 23.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>For,</p>
            <q>
               <p>The righteous hath hope in his Death.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 14.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quanta eſt felicitaes eorum! quam immenſa latitia, qui, nimirum. tripl ei gaudie. De recerdatione tranſacta virtutis. De exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitione pro entis quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s. De certa expectatione ſutura conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationis, exultant!</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern, Serm. 2. in feſto omnium San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Ratcliffe,</hi> and <hi>N. Thompſon,</hi> for <hi>B. Southwood</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> next to <hi>Serjeants-Inn</hi> in <hi>Chancery-lane.</hi> 1672.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing it is a thing generally known &amp; acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whereof none can plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that it is appointed for men once to die: (for the living know that they muſt die, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.5.) And ſeeing the time of death
<pb facs="tcp:34925:4"/>
is generally to men moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and the Word of God aſſures, <hi>that after Death there will be a Judgment, in which every man muſt give an account of himſelf to God, and receive according to the things done in the Body whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or evil, Heb.</hi> 9.27. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Seeing alſo fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the ſame infallible word of the living God, who hath given us life and breath, and all things, and hath us and our breath in his hands, declares to us that He of his great mercy hath deviſed and made a way, though not to eſcape this bodily Death, yet whereby we may ſtand in the
<pb facs="tcp:34925:4"/>
Judgment and receive the doom and Sentence of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting and moſt bleſſed life: which way if it be neglected, there will inſue an everlaſting ſtate of wo and miſery. It muſt needs follow, that it is of greateſt moment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to All to enquire after, and ſet their heart to that way and device, making it their greateſt work and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, whatever elſe is negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that they may lay hold on that eternal life, and avoid that miſery. Yea, and foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the time of this uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain life is the whole of the time allotted for our preparing for the Judgment, it behoves
<pb facs="tcp:34925:5"/>
every man to take heed of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending it, and to be careful to redeem it, and diligently improve it, to make ſure of Happineſs in Eternity, not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinating to ſeek after God: nor preſuming upon Gods pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and longer continuance in the Land of the living. Which things being conſidered it muſt needs be by all thought and acknowledged, that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes of this nature are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſeaſonable, and if any thing well done, worthy acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance. Diſcourſes, I ſay, upon ſuch a Subject as I here propound to preſent thee with, namely, ſuch as ſhew the Happineſs to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
<pb facs="tcp:34925:5"/>
notwithſtanding Death; and the way how we may be brought to the enjoyment thereof, and to be ſecured againſt the Fears of Death: or what harms or miſchiefs will otherwiſe be occaſioned by it to us. I cannot, I confeſs, commend the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of my performance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſerious and weighty a Subject which deſerves a far larger and more preſſing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and hath alſo obtained it by ſome more Reverend and Learned hands.</p>
            <p>What I here preſent was not in the leaſt intended in my firſt conſideration of it, or writing upon it for the
<pb facs="tcp:34925:6"/>
Preſs, onely to ſatisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of a loving Friend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned mainly in the occaſion of its conſideration, I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make it publick. And ſuch as it is commend it to Gods bleſſing, and thy peruſal. Praying it may be both for my own and thy future and eternal benefit, and reſting a ſervant to thee and all men, for Jeſus ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Horn.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 8. 1671/2.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34925:6"/>
            <head>A Comfortable Corroborative Cordial: Or, A Sovereign Antidote againſt, and Preſervative from, the Horrours and Harms of DEATH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 14.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, Write, Bleſſed are the Dead that die in the Lord from henceforth, Yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur Lord Jeſus Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (after many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of great concernment to his Churches) ſhewed by his Angel to his ſervant <hi>John,</hi> in the twelfth Chapter, the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Dragon (or Devil and Sathan) firſt in the <hi>Roman</hi> Pagan Empire againſt Chriſt and his Church, and his dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34925:7"/>
or caſting down from Heaven (from his ſtate of being worſhipped as a Deity) and after that in his ſtirring up a flood of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and hereſies to carry away the Church with, and how God preſerved her againſt them. And in the thirteenth Chapter, the troubles and perſecutions that Sathan would further raiſe againſt his Church by a two-fold Antichriſtian perſecuting power called Beaſts, ſetting up and managing a corrupt Worſhip, and perſecuting its refuſers. In this Chapter ſhews him divers things tending to animate his ſervants in their conſtancy againſt them. As to ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. He ſhewed him the <hi>Lamb,</hi> (Chriſt himſelf) <hi>ſtanding</hi> (ſafe and unmoved for all his enemies) <hi>upon mount Sion</hi> (where God had ſet him as King, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.5. a place which cannot be moved, but ſtands faſt for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.1. and 11.4.) <hi>and with him</hi> (in the ſame ſure ſtate) <hi>an hundred four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four thouſand</hi> (the number of the ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chap. 7.) <hi>having his Fathers name</hi> (not the Beaſts, either Authority or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine) <hi>written in their foreheads</hi> (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and boldly avowed yet by them)</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2. And made him hear <hi>a voice from heaven as the voice of many waters,</hi> (as loud, evident and certain, as if many peoples, nations, and languages compared
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34925:7"/>
to many waters, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 17:12. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. had atteſted the things ſpoken as eye-witneſſes thereof) <hi>and as the voice of a great thunder</hi> (ſignifying their boldneſs in Chriſt, and dreadfulneſs to their enemies) and a <hi>voice of harpers harping with harps.</hi> (as rejoycing in their victory over their enemies, as was the cuſtome in Iſrael to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize their Victories with muſical inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as in <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.20. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18 6. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.28)</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>And they ſung a new ſong</hi> (as ſuch ſongs of praiſes upon eſcapes of dangers, and upon victories are ſtiled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.3. and 98.1) <hi>before the Throne and before the four living creatures</hi> (was badly tranſlated Beaſts, that is in ſhort, before God and his Church) <hi>And no man could learn that ſong but the hundred fourty and four thouſand which were redeemed from the earth</hi> (either from the love of earthly things through the efficacy of Gods grace eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the blood of Chriſt; or alſo taken from the earth by Death, Peculiar ſervices, ſufferings, and ſucceſſes againſt Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies have their peculiar joyes not common to others. Then ſhewing,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. What ones theſe redeemed ones were, he adds: <hi>Theſe are they that were not defiled with women</hi> (with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34925:8"/>
and Aſſemblies of corrupt Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Idolaters, and their corruptions in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Worſhip, compared to women or harlots, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.13. and 14.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. <hi>for they are virgins</hi> (chaſt and ſingle to Chriſt his Faith and Worſhip) <hi>theſe follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth</hi> (that is, they cleave in all things to Chriſt, and his word, and commands, and are not moved therefrom by any falſe pretences of the falſe Prophet or two-horned Beaſt, and his falſe and lying miracles; nor by the greatneſs and dreadfulneſs of the ſeven headed and ten-horned Beaſt, and their contrary commands) <hi>for theſe were redeemed</hi> (powerfully through the grace of God believed by them, brought out unto Chriſt) <hi>from among men</hi> (from the idolatrous and wicked world, to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God) <hi>being the firſt fruits</hi> (moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable and pleaſing, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.1.) <hi>to God and to the Lamb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Verſ. 4. <hi>And in their mouth was found no guile</hi> (they were upright and orthodox Chriſtians, not diſſembling with men to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void perſecutions) <hi>for they are without fault before the Throne of God. (Nathaniels</hi> or Iſraelites indeed in whom there is no guile, believers in Chriſt, and walkers after his Spirit, and ſo in the light as God is in the light directing and ſtrengthning them, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34925:8"/>
therefore there is no condemnation to them, but the blood of Chriſt cleanſing them from all ſin they have fellowſhip with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. The truſters in God, and unmovable as mount Sion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.1. But let none imagine that Chriſt died onely for theſe and ſuch like, becauſe called <hi>redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ones,</hi> but mind that he adds</p>
            <p n="6">6. Verſ 4. <hi>I ſaw another Angel flying in the midſt of heaven</hi> (moſt openly) <hi>having the Everlaſting Goſpel to preach to them that dwell on</hi> (not yet redeemed from) <hi>the earth, and to every nation, kindred, tongue, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> As the Angels ſometime appeared clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in linen like the Prieſts in the Temple, as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Rev,</hi> 15.6. So the holy Prieſthood or Goſpel Preachers may be here denoted by Angels, and here is Goſpel preached to others beſides thoſe redeemed ones, even to all people; but there is no Goſpel for any for whom Chriſt died not, and for whom in him no help or ſalvation: therefore Chriſts death is not to be limited to, or meaſured by, ſuch expreſſions as thoſe in the foregoing verſes, or that in Chap. 5.9. The ſum of the Goſpel to be preached, is that in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6. that God wills <hi>that all men be ſaved and come to the knowledge of the Truth: for there is one God and one Mediatour of God and men, the man Chriſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34925:9"/>
Jeſus, who gave himſelf a ranſome for all, a teſtimony,</hi> (or this is the teſtimony) in due times; whereunto the Apoſtle ſaith, He was <hi>ordained a Preacher and Apoſtle,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>the Everlaſting Gospel,</hi> and therefore Goſpel in all ages as well as then. Other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the ſum of the Goſpel, ſee in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. <hi>The being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the earth and from among men</hi> is a further buſineſs, at leaſt an effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al product of the grace of God believed in mens hearts and conſciences, as is fore-hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but this Angel in Preaching the Goſpel <hi>ſaid with a loud voice,</hi> (what the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel loudly ſpeaks to be the duty of all men, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Verſ. 7. <hi>Fear God, and give glory to him, for the hour of his judgment is come,</hi> (not unlike that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.8, 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30, 31. though it may here have ſome ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al eye at the ruine of <hi>Babylon</hi> preſently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted) <hi>and worſhip him that made heaven, and earth, and the ſea, and the fountains of waters;</hi> (expreſſions like thoſe which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith was the ſum or end of their preaching, in <hi>Acts</hi> 14.15. but after this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows)</p>
            <p n="8">8. Verſ. 8. <hi>And another Angel followed, ſaying, Babylon is fallen, is fallen</hi> (the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling expreſſion implies its certainty and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34925:9"/>
ſpeedineſs, and the joy of Gods holy ones at it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.32. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20.) <hi>that great city</hi> (the oppoſite to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the holy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or true Church of God) <hi>becauſe ſhe made all nations drink of the wine of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications. (Babylon</hi> is the then <hi>ruling City over the kings of the earth, Rev.</hi> 17.18. which was <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo denotes that idolatrous Church, called the Whore for her being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted from Chriſt, and the ſincere Faith and worſhip of him, forſaking her fidelity to him to follow after and proſtitute her ſelf to the Kings of the earth, ſeeking and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their favour, riches, gifts, honour, defence <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet (as Harlots uſe to do with their Paramours <hi>Jud.</hi> 16.6, 20.) ordering and ruling them as ſhe liſts, pretending that ſhe is the Lady and Queen of Heaven; that onely Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church from whom they muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all their Faith, Worſhip and Religion, and it may be noted that her downfal, and ſo of all Idolatry, Hereſie and falſe worſhip, either is and will be the effect (not of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Rebellions, but) of the ſincere and bold Preaching the Goſpel of Chriſt with its inſtructions by holy living; or Angel-like perſons, <hi>not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord, Zech.</hi> 4.6.) or will otherwiſe joyn, and follow after it.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 9, 10, 11. After theſe, Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34925:10"/>
ſhewed him a third Angel that followed, and warned of the danger of worſhipping the Beaſt (eſpecially after the Goſpel preached and the fall of <hi>Babylon</hi> denounced) <hi>ſaying with a loud voice, If any man worſhip the Beaſt or his Image, and receive his mark in his forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture into the cup of his indignation, and ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb: And the ſmoke of their torment aſcendeth up for ever and ever. And they have no reſt day nor night who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the mark of his name.</hi> A dreadful Sentence that might awaken all to enquire what this <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image, Mark</hi> and <hi>Name</hi> are, and what the worſhip thus threatened, and carefully avoid all things thereof. I ſhall onely here ſay, it's the preferring ſome other powers above Chriſt, and ſo is the ſame in ſubſtance with that. <hi>Curſed</hi> is <hi>the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm, and his heart departeth from the Lord Jer.</hi> 17.5. but that that time will be ſad, is ſignified in the following exclamation, whether of the Angel or Evangeliſt, which ſaith,</p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>Verſ</hi> 12. <hi>Here is the patience of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34925:10"/>
Saints.</hi> here at this time moſt eminently tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and exerciſed. <hi>Here are they</hi> (emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally) <hi>that keep the commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus, and forſake them not for the Beaſt Worſhip;</hi> but then to hearten unto thoſe ſufferings though to death, he addes in the Text.</p>
            <p>Ver. 14. <hi>And I heard a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying, Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. from the following whereof ſo immediately upon the former intimation, we may note Chriſts great care of his Church; as when he formerly told his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of weeping and mourning, he preſently tells them too of what might ſupport them, and bear up their ſorrowful hearts from ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: When he tells them he muſt leave them, he tells them alſo, that he would ſee them again, and not leave them comfortleſs, or as Orphans; and that upon his ſeeing them again, their hearts ſhould rejoyce, and their joy ſhould no man take from them; and that in him they ſhould have peace, who had alſo overcome the world, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.20, 21, 22, 23. And when the Lord ſpeaks of the like ſad things with theſe by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah; That all the beaſts would come to devour, his watchmen being blind, and the ſhepherds void of underſtanding; ſo that the righteous periſh, no man regarding it, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34925:11"/>
men are taken away from the evil:</hi> Yet then alſo for encouraging the hearts of his ſuffering ſervants, he proclaims like things with theſe here, even the ſweet and excellent ſtate of thoſe righteous &amp; merciful men, when ſo taken away and periſhed from among men, that is, when Dead: <hi>He ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall lie in their beds, each one walking in his uprightneſs;</hi> while he threatens judgment to the ſeed of the ſorcereſs, the ſeed of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer, and of the whore, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.9, 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 57.1, 2, 3. Though our Lord leads his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o afflictions becauſe he ſees them needful and uſeful for them, yet he would not have them faint under their afflictions, to deprive themſelves of the good intended by them. His Word and Goſpel occaſion trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to them from the world, while they are thereby drawn out of the world, and are led to teſtifie of him to, and againſt the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the world: but he provides com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and ſupports for them by the ſame word, by, and for which they ſuffer, that they might be inabled patiently to endure the things which they muſt ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Yea, and we may further note from this Voice and Proclamation of the bleſſed ſtate of the dead that die in the Lord, following ſo immediately after that acclamation, <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints;</hi> That the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34925:11"/>
of the happy ſtate of the dead in Chriſt, is an excellent motive to a patient continuance in well-doing, though ſuffering for it unto death: <hi>Rejoycing in hope firſt, we may be patient in tribulation,</hi> Rom. 12.12. Did we expect ſtill a continuance of evils in Death, and that it would make us ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy and miſerable; and that Death is the end and recompence of an holy life from the world, it would exceedingly damp and take off the courage of men from exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing patience, and continuing to keep the Commandments of God, and the faith of Jeſus: But being rooted and grounded in the Faith, and not moved from the hope of the Goſpel, we may be there through ſtrengthned to all long ſuffering, and patience with joyfulneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.11.23.</p>
            <p>The words themſelves are a command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and we have thereabout,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The perſon acquainted with it, <hi>I,</hi> the holy Apoſtle or Pen-man of theſe Viſions: <hi>Surely the Lord God will do nothing, but he reveals his ſecret unto his ſervants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> Amos 3.7. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with thoſe that fear him,</hi> &amp;c. Pſal. 25.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The way of his perceiving or receiving it; and that was by the ear, at leaſt the ear of his Spirit. <hi>I heard. God ſpeaks once and twice, and man regards it not, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34925:12"/>
it not,</hi> Job 33.14. But bleſſed are the ears of his Diſciples, for they hear, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 13.16.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The way of its being conveyed to him, and that was by a voice: Sound or voice are the proper ways of conveying things to the ear, and by the ear to the mind; and a voice is but an articulate ſound. There may be voice where there is no hearing, as above is ſignified in <hi>Job</hi> 33.14, &amp;c. And as is ſaid of the Levites wife when dead, <hi>Judg.</hi> 19.25. and of the Shunammits ſon, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.31. But there can be no hearing without ſome ſound or voice.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We have the place whence it came from heaven. Which being the place of Gods moſt glorious Reſidence, and Manifeſtation of himſelf; and where our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the holy and juſt one, is on the Throne of Majeſty; and where only holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the ſpirits of juſt men have place: But no evil Angel, Satan being caſt out thence, nor no unclean thing may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to enter: We may be ſure no voice comes from thence, but what is holy and true, and ſuch as is worthy to be received with all acceptation, being ſupremely and originally the voice of God, and of our Lord Jeſus, though it might be inſtrumentally ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by ſome holy Angel. And ſo the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34925:12"/>
Command here, was a Command of God and Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We have the perſon to whom it was directed; and that was to the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: <hi>I heard a voice from heaven ſaying unto me.</hi> He heard divers voices in and from heaven not directed to him, as may be ſeen <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.2, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. Voices di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Chriſt, ſome to God, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.5. 7. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 19.1.5, 6, 7. Some to the people of God, <hi>Chap</hi> 18.4. but this was directed to this Saint <hi>John</hi> himſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have,</p>
            <p n="6">6. The matter of the Voice, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it ſelf; and therein,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Act commanded him, and that was to write; <hi>Saying to me, Write.</hi> And this was an exerciſe that God employed divers of his holy Servants in, but is not univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally the work and buſineſs of all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or of thoſe that are accepted of him: as all are not Apoſtles, nor all Prophets, nor all Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 28, 29, 30. ſo neither are, or have all his Servants been ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pen-men of Holy Scriptures, or of other Divine Matters; but as the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit diſtributes his ſundry Gifts variouſly, ſo hath he given commands to ſome to ſpeak, to others to write the heavenly Truths. But neither the one nor the other ſo generally as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34925:13"/>
the hearing of them; this was an honour put upon his Servants according as he pleaſed for others uſefulneſs. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was employed to ſpeak, and <hi>Baruch</hi> to write the words from his mouth. <hi>Jer.</hi> 36.17, 18 <hi>Moſes</hi> did both write and ſpeak to the people the words of the Law, and Commands of God, and of the Song he was to put into the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mouths, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.9, 19, 22, 24, 30. Yea, this Gift of Writing is an excellent Gift of God, a way of conveying his Truths, and of his great works and doings which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath made uſe of; as he wrote the Ten Commandments with his own hand or finger, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10 1, 2 4. and many of his holy Prophets, and the Evangeliſts, and Apoſtles, divers of them were employed in this Exerciſe, whoſe Writing he owns alſo as his own, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith, <hi>Have not I written to thee excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things,</hi> Prov. 22.20. <hi>And I have written to them the great things of my Law,</hi> Hoſ. 8.12.</p>
            <p>And it may be minded, yea, and muſt be acknowledged, that in ſome reſpects this way of conveying over knowledge unto men, hath the preheminence in divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects above that of ſpeech; both as</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be preſerved a longer time what is this way imparted; when as the voice of words paſs away into the air, after they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34925:13"/>
are uttered: and ſo knowledge may be, and hath been tranſmitted this way to after ages and generations, long after thoſe that have uttered thoſe truths by words of mouth are dead and gone. And this uſe of Writing, or end of Gods making uſe of it, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding it to be uſed, is expreſly ſignified by himſelf; for not onely did <hi>Moſes</hi> write the Law, and deliver it to the Prieſts, as a means to acquaint with it, and with the works of God therein mentioned, thoſe that had not known them, even the children to be born, commanding them to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe at the end of every ſeven years to read it to all the people, men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the ſtrangers within their gates, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.10, 11, 12, 13. but alſo God ordered <hi>Moſes</hi> to write the Song menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the ſame Chapter, that it might be a witneſs for him againſt the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> that it might not be forgotten out of the mouths of their ſeed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19.21. And the Lord bade <hi>Iſaiah</hi> go write it on a Table, and note it in a Book, that it might be for the time to come (or for the latter day) even for ever and ever, <hi>that this is a rebellious people,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.8.9. See alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.18.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This way the knowledge of things, and of Gods Works and Words, may be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34925:14"/>
made known to many more then they can by any ones audible voice be declared to, as in all theſe Nations we have this way the declarations of thoſe things brought to us that were done in <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi> and the words ſpoken in thoſe places are this way brought to our cognizance; yea, by this way things ſpoken in ſecret, yea, or when we can have no opportunity to ſpeak our minds to any body, what we would ſpeak may be conveyed abroad, and made publick; and things ſpoken in the ear (as divers of our Saviours Parables) may be publiſhed all over the World. Yea, and</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is a more ſafe and certain way of conveyance of knowledge. Words may be miſtaken and miſrelated by thoſe that hear, and would relate them: many things in that way may be, and often have been, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, omitted, or altered. But what it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten remains fixed, and may without addition, omiſſion, or alteration be read and tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. Thence it is ſaid, <hi>I have written to thee excellent things, that I might make thee know the certainty of the words of truth; and that thou mayeſt anſwer the words of truth to thoſe that ſend to thee,</hi> Prov. 22.20, 21. Bleſs we God for ſo excellent and uſeful a gift, and for the great good things made known to us thereby, and take we heed of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34925:14"/>
abuſing, or being harmed by it; for as God ordered it for great good and profit to men, ſo Sathan who can create nothing himſelf but lyes, abuſes, and leads his followers to abuſe this (as all other gifts of God) to Gods diſhonour, and mens deſtruction: and ſcarce any ſo much as this while it is made uſe of to propagate and keep on foot all manner of lyes and miſchievous devices: as is too evident.</p>
            <p>But now, as every Act muſt have its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or matter about which it is exerciſed, ſo this writing muſt be of ſomething to be written. And indeed the thing that God commanded to be written, is generally ſomething, both true, as it is ſaid, <hi>That which was written was upright, even words of truth,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.10. As alſo the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the things concerning the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to be written, addes this as a reaſon; <hi>For theſe words are faithful and true,</hi> Rev. 21.5. And alſo of weight and uſefulneſs for the generations and people to whom they are ordered, and for whoſe ſake written; and ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that we through patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Scriptures might have hope,</hi> Rom. 15.4. and <hi>they were written for our admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.11. and <hi>write the viſion, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34925:15"/>
make it plain upon tables, that he may run that reads it.</hi> That he may be encouraged and ſtrengthend <hi>to run with patience the race ſet before him,</hi> Habak. 2.2. And ſo here is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The matter to be written, ſome faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and uſeful matter to be preſerved for the benefit of after ages. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. Wherein there is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. A heavenly Oracle, Doctrine, or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Dead that dye in the Lord are henceforth bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Confirmation of this Aſſertion or Doctrine. And that both,
<list>
                  <item>1. By Authority or Teſtimony; the higheſt, greateſt, and moſt indiſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, <hi>Yea, ſaith the Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By Proof, or Demonſtration, or Reaſon alledged; and that alſo is two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>That they may reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>And their works do follow them, or follow with them.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall endeavour to conſider them briefly in this order, with ſome Application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Doctrine commanded to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and accordingly written, is, <hi>That the Dead that dye in the Lord henceforth are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34925:15"/>
bleſſed, or are henceforth bleſſed.</hi> Wherein we have,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſubject of the Aſſertion, or that whereabout it is; and that is, <hi>The Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A qualification of this Subject, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it the proper Subject aſſerted of; and that is, <hi>That dye in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The thing aſſerted or theſe; and that is, <hi>That they are bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The time from whence either the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject aſſerted of, or the thing aſſerted of them commenceth; for it may be either way conſtrued: either the dead that dye in the Lord henceforth, and ſo it's a more ſpecial limitation of the Subject aſſerted of; or, the Dead that dye in the Lord (generally or whenſoever) are henceforth bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject is the Dead, not the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. And this term (the Dead) is ſpoken of variouſly in the Scriptures, according to a various way of dying; as there are that are dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, but they are not bleſſed, &amp; therefore not here meant, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.18. And there are that are dead to ſin, and ought ſo to reckon themſelves, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. And dead to the Law, for ſeeking righteouſneſs thereby, and having their hope and confidence therefrom, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19, 20. And theſe are in a ſenſe bleſſed, or in the way to it. And there are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34925:16"/>
that are dead in the body, and as to natural life; as <hi>Abraham</hi> is dead, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets be dead, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.52. And that is the ſenſe of the words here. Thence note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note</hi> 1. That bodily Death and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be conſiſtent; men that dye, and are dead, may be bleſſed: Not onely thoſe that are dead to the Law by the Body of Chriſt delivered from the curſe of that, and from being under it as the Covenant of Life; or that are dead to ſin, or rather perſons not onely dead in thoſe conſiderations, but alſo that are bodily dead, may be happy, in a very good, ſafe, and deſirable condition; ſo as that their ſtate may worthily be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended as very excellent: They may have their ſins forgiven and blotted out, and they that are in that condition are bleſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.12. They may have the favour of God, and be accepted and beloved of him, and they that are ſo, are bleſſed, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34, 35. and (which includes both the former) they may have God to be their God, and to own them as his people, as it is ſaid of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> long after they were dead and buried; <hi>I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob,</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. 3.6.15. And <hi>bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 144.15. And forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſins, and the favour of God are both
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34925:16"/>
implied to be the portion of thoſe Souls ſeen in viſion under the Altar, even the Souls of thoſe that had been ſlain for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony that they held, in that there were white Robes given to every one of them, as a token both of their free and full acquittance from ſin, and their being owned of God as righteous ones, and alſo of their being highly honoured and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>And this not a little takes off the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this bodily Death, that it may conſiſt with Bleſſedneſs; and that it is not of it ſelf able to hinder and deprive us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Men may be happy notwithſtanding its power and force. That's the dreadful Death, that men cannot be happy in, or under ſuch as the death in Sin, the ſpiritual death of the Soul under the guilt and power of ſin committed and continued in; and therefore that is threatened as a very ſad evil to be ſhunned. To be carnally minded, or the minding of the fleſh is death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6. a ſtate not to be continued in where it is, nor by any means to be run into where men are delivered therefrom: As alſo, The ſecond Death, the ſeparation of the Soul, or of the whole man rather from God in Soul and Body for ever; the everlaſting fire or lake burning with fire and brimſtone, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34925:17"/>
portion of the Devil and his Angels, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. This is a ſad and dreadful ſtate indeed, namely this of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death: While men are ſpiritually dead in ſin, their ſins are imputed, and they have no fellowſhip with God; but yet while alive in the body, they are in a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of being called and made alive to God, to him that's joyned to all the living there is hope, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.6. But in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Death is nothing but miſery without hope of remedy or redemption; This, this is the Death then with all diligence to be ſhunned, and therefore care is to be taken to awake out of ſin alſo by repentance; for death in ſin continued in, brings the ſecond Death inevitably upon men. But as for this bodily Death, that's not ſo dreadful in it ſelf; men may do well for all that: and the reaſon is, becauſe Chriſt hath died for us, and is riſen again. This death indeed, as it was in its firſt threatning, and as upon our deſert incurred by us in the Fall of our firſt Parents, deprived us of all Bleſſedneſs, and would inevitably have done ſo for ever, had not God provided a deliverer; and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from it, had not he graciouſly deviſed a device that his baniſhed might not be expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for ever from him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.14. <hi>But bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, who hath
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34925:17"/>
raiſed up an Horn of ſalvation for us in the houſe of his ſervant David,</hi> that by him we might be <hi>ſaved from our enemies; that hath given his onely begotten Son to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſins that we might live through him,</hi> Luk. 1.68, 69, 70. 1 Joh. 4.9.10. And bleſſed be the Son of God that willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly took upon himſelf in compliance with his Fathers will to ſuffer and die for us, that we through his ſtripes might be healed of that deadly wound wherewith in our liſtning to the Serpent, we were wounded by him, he having giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n himſelf the ranſome for all, and taſted Death by the grace of God, for every man; hath aboliſhed or taken away the deſtructive power of this Death; and deſtroyed through his Death, him that had the power of it, that is the Devil; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raiſed again from the dead he hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained even all redemption of all mankind from out this Death, ſo as none of them ſhall finally periſh therein, but be all raiſed out thereof: <hi>for as by man</hi> (Adam) <hi>came death: even by man</hi> (even the man Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>comes the reſurrection of the dead: for as in Adam all die: ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. He is the reſurrection and the life, and through him there is an open paſſage now
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34925:18"/>
made through this death, and all the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, concomitants and conſequences of it to life and immortality, even to eternal life, in which is, and ſtands the onely true bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>In Chriſt there is given us</hi> (even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mankind generally conſidered) <hi>eternal life,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11. in him the righteouſneſs of God is for, or unto all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22. and the <hi>free gift unto all men for the juſtification of life, Rom.</hi> 5 18. In him is forgiveneſs of ſins, and plenteouſneſs of Redemption through his blood, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.4.5. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1.14. and therefore by means of him men may be brought back to God, and enjoy him, his favour, and Kingdom notwithſtanding this death, yea in the very ſtate of it, and while actually dead they may be bleſſed. Bleſs we God for this gracious Device and doing of his for us, in, and by Chriſt; and bleſs we Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, that he hath ſo acted and wrought through his Croſs for us; and imbrace we the glad tidings of it with all acceptation and thankfulneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But yet, In that the Holy Spirit ſtopt not there at <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead,</hi> but adds a reſtrictive, diſtinctive qualification, ſaying, <hi>The Dead that die in the Lord.</hi> Learn we thence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> Secondly, That though this bodily <hi>death</hi> &amp; <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> may ſtand &amp; be together,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34925:18"/>
yet all that die this Death or are dead in it are not bleſſed. No, we cannot ſay ſo, there be many that dye, and are dead in the Body, that ſhall never meet with bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, though bleſsedneſs may be met with notwithſtanding this death. We read of two men that dyed this Death, the one bleſſed and the other curſed; the Rich man, and <hi>Lazarus: Lazarus</hi> was bleſſed and happy, being carried of the Angels into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> boſom; but the Rich man was moſt miſerably wretched, being carried into Hell, and there grievouſly tormented; without ſo much relief or hope of poſſibility of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much relief, as might amount to or be reſembled by a <hi>drop of water to cool his tongue, Luke</hi> 16.19.25, 26. and we find mention of a multitude, nay, of diverſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with their multitudes gone down into the Pit of deſtruction in their uncircumciſedneſs, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.18.30, 31. and our Saviour tells us of Gods <hi>killing the body and casting into Hell. Luke</hi> 12 5. and that <hi>the Gate is wide and the Way broad that leads to Deſtruction,</hi> and that <hi>many go in thereat, Matth.</hi> 7.13. for the many dye in their ſins, and that's a ſad dying, and is mentioned as ſuch by our Saviour, when he ſaith to the Jews, <hi>I go my way and ye ſhall ſeek me, and dye in your ſins, whither I go</hi> (and that was to heaven
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34925:19"/>
to his Father) <hi>ye cannot come. Ye are of this world, I am not of this world. I ſaid therefore that ye ſhall dye in your ſins, for if ye believe not that I am He, ye ſhall dye in your ſins, Joh</hi> 8.21, 24. And indeed that's the onely thing that makes any miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable that are dead: that they dyed in their ſins, and their ſins lie down with them in the duſt, as is ſaid, <hi>Job</hi> 20.11. For where ſin is continued in and not repented of, there it is not pardoned; and where ſin is not pardoned, men are not bleſſed, but curſed. But this proceeds not from the force of the firſt or bodily death, but from the wilfulneſs and careleſneſs of men, while they be here alive; in neglecting Chriſt and the grace in him, and the ſalvation tendered to them; in that when He by his wiſdom calls men to himſelf, and offers to make them wiſe and to ſave them; as is abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifyed in <hi>Prov.</hi> 81.4, 5. and 9.1.4.5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. yea, and counſels them to what is good, and reproves their contrary courſes, and neglects or rejections of his Counſels, and waits upon them with long-ſuffering, yet they refuſe and ſleight all his love and good will, and harden their hearts againſt all means and methods in inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and chaſtiſements tending to their good: as is ſignified <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22, 23, 24,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34925:19"/>
25.29, 30. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.9, 10, 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39, 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is true that Chriſt dyed for all, even while ſinners; for the ungodly and enemies, and thereby hath ranſomed them from under the firſt Judgement, and from the lordſhip of Sathan into his own power and diſpoſe, as is ſignified, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. and 14.9. yea, and hath obtained into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf all fulneſs of grace and bleſſing: So as in him all the Families of the earth are bleſſed; <hi>that is,</hi> abundantly provided for of all things tending to, and ſufficient to render them bleſſed in the participation thereof; ſo as he is repreſented as a full and large <hi>feaſt prepared for all people, Iſa.</hi> 25.6. being the Salvation <hi>prepared</hi> of God <hi>before the face of</hi> (or over againſt the needs of) <hi>all people, Luke</hi> 2.31. as a like phraſe ſignifies and is equivalently rendered in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18. and having wrought a perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which is <hi>for,</hi> unto all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.22. But yet men cannot receive the benefit of all this, but in receiving, ſubmitting to, and obeying: even as the Feaſt prepared pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited not thoſe that were invited to it and refuſed to come; nay they refuſing it, and therein ſleighting the love of him that made it and called them to it, provoked new an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and wrath to their deſtruction, <hi>Matth.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:34925:20"/>
22.4.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 14, 16, 17.24. the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neglected, is a healing medicine refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and not taken, which leaves the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, like perſons deſperately diſeaſed, in that caſe, to die of their Diſeaſe without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy or eſcape. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1, 3. the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs for all comes upon <hi>all that believe;</hi> and therefore it being through unbelief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, is like the <hi>Weeding garment</hi> not put on, which neither clothes nor warms the perſon refuſing it, nor makes him comely and lovely; but being not on a man, the mans nakedneſs and unhandſomneſs, together with the refuſal of the Charity ſhewed and proffered in preparing it for, and offering it to him, lays the perſon open to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled (though come into Gods houſe) and to be <hi>caſt out into outer darkneſs, Rom.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.10, 11, 12, 13. the <hi>Life Eternal given us in Christ</hi> is ſo given in and with him, that he that hath him, he only hath and enjoys it; and he that rejects and hath not Him, hath not it, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. To the enjoyment of Bleſſedneſs then, there muſt be a receiving and obedience to Chriſt, the Fountain and treaſury of it; otherwiſe, though men periſh not in the firſt Death, they will and muſt in the ſecond: for <hi>the ſoul that ſinneth</hi> (that ſtill and perpetually or impenitently ſinneth) though it <hi>die not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34925:20"/>
for the Fathers iniquity,</hi> nor have its <hi>teeth ſet on edge, becauſe</hi> its <hi>Father</hi> Adam <hi>eat</hi> the forbidden <hi>ſowre grape,</hi> and ſo <hi>the ſon ſhall not bear the fathers iniquity;</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb before mentioned with reference to the ſecond and Eternal Death, ſhall not take place, <hi>yet for its own ſinning it ſhall die, Ezek.</hi> 18.2, 3, 4.19, 20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.29, 30.</p>
            <p>The dealings of God here are ſomewhat anſwerable to his dealings with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when <hi>having brought them all out of Egypt</hi> (not leaving Man nor mothers Child, nor any Hoof there) yet <hi>He afterward deſtroyed them that believed not, for their unbelief</hi> and rebellious <hi>ſinning</hi> and going on to ſin <hi>againſt him in the Wilderneſs, Jude</hi> 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.17, 18. even ſo here, it's not the firſt Death and Judgment detains any; but yet Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bought all into his diſpoſe from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that, will afterward judge to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death thoſe that believe or obey not. It is not any want of merit or worthineſs in Chriſts Death, or excluſion of them from being of its object, nor want of fulneſs or readineſs in him for ſaving them; but <hi>this is the condemnation, that Light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light Joh.</hi> 3.19. Onely Death, this bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Death puts an end to the time of Gods patient waiting for their coming to Chriſt,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34925:21"/>
cloſing with his Light and Love, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting of their ſins, and finding mercy with him. All the time God continues mens lives here, there is a poſſibility of eſcaping the Wrath to come: <hi>For God is patient towards us not willing any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. Yea, <hi>his goodneſs and forbearance</hi> is inviting <hi>and leading men to repentance, Rom.</hi> 2.4. and is to be <hi>accounted Salvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 15. Even <hi>Jezabel</hi> while Chriſt ſpared her he <hi>gave her space to repent,</hi> though <hi>ſhe repented not, Rev.</hi> 2.21. yea, and when he threatens to <hi>caſt her into a Bed, and them that commit adultery with her, even into great tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yet it is with this Proviſo mentioned, <hi>Except they repent of their deeds,</hi> verſ. 22. ſo ſlow is God to anger, and ſo lothe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude men from bliſs and happineſs, and ſo ready to ſhew mercy and to forgive, and ſo agreeable are Gods dealings to his Word and Oath, wherein he ſaith, and ſweares to it, that <hi>as He lives he hath no pleaſure</hi> (none at all ſecret or revealed) <hi>in the Death of the wicked, but rather that he turn and live, Ezech.</hi> 33 11. <hi>To him that is joyned to all the living there is hope, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.4. And Chriſt <hi>Dyed for all, that they that live</hi> (while yet they live) <hi>ſhould not henceforth live to themſelves, but to him that Dyed for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34925:21"/>
them and roſe again,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. But now when Death ſeizes on a man and cuts him off, then the door is ſhut upon him, and ſhould he now ſtand without and knock, it is too late; the anſwer from within is, <hi>I know you not: Depart from me ye workers of iniquity;</hi> No opening then, nor any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.25, 26, 27. the <hi>Feaſt</hi> ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſhall not</hi> then <hi>be taſted of</hi> for ever by them, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.24. thence <hi>the Gulf is for ever fixed</hi> ſo that there is no coming of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from Heaven to help them: nor no go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their ſtate of Miſery to a ſtate of Salvation, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. <hi>in the Grave whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we go there is no work, nor device: no knowledge or wiſdom,</hi> for the helpfulneſs of any that have here neglected Gods work and device declared to them, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and wiſdom here offered them, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. Now is the accepted time; now is the day of Salvation, now is the day for men to hear in, and to work the works of God in; but if this be ſleighted, and men harden their hearts now, and will not hear Gods voice, <hi>the night comes</hi> and will come upon them <hi>wherein no man can work;</hi> after which there will be no more day, except an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Judgment upon them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſtate of Death, they that dye in their ſins are ſo far from being happy and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34925:22"/>
bleſſed, that they are far more wretched then, then before; for though they are not bleſſed while here, becauſe their ſins are not blotted out, yet there is a poſſibility they may be ſo, and there is yet ſuch a mercy held forth to them as obtainable by them; <hi>for if the wicked man will turn from all his ſins that he hath committed and keep all</hi> Gods <hi>ſtatutes, and do that which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and right,</hi> if he will liſten to and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on Chriſt Jeſus, and not walk any longer after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit, there ſhall be no longer any Condemnation to him, <hi>He ſtall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye;</hi> namely, the ſecond Death, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21. <hi>all his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed they ſhall not be mentioned to him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. But when dead in his ſins, then there is no more hope or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of being happy; He who was miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable before under a poſſibility of mercy, is now endleſly and remedileſly miſerable without that poſſibility. Oh! therefore how doth it behove every one now to ſtrive to <hi>enter in at the ſtrait gate, Luke</hi> 13.24. to <hi>do what his hands find him to do with all his might,</hi> for ſeeking mercy and favour with God, <hi>ſeeking the Lord while he may be found,</hi> and <hi>calling upon him while he is nigh at hand, Iſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34925:22"/>
               <hi>while it is</hi> yet ſaid, or <hi>called to day, not hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the heart</hi> but hearkening to Gods voice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.7.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.7, 8, 15. making <hi>haſte</hi> and not delaying <hi>to keep Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Pſal</hi> 119.59, 60. haſting to eſcape (as the Angels ſaid to <hi>Lot</hi> when they brought him and his Family out of <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 19.17.) as for our lives or ſouls <hi>not looking back,</hi> ſtaying or lingring in all the Plain of this World, <hi>but eſcape to the mountain</hi> of the Lord <hi>left we be conſumed,</hi> giving di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to know, win and be found in Chriſt Jeſus: and being brought in to him, to abide in him and be faithful to him to the Death, and then no danger of being miſerable for ever: For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they that dye in the Lord from henceforth.</hi> And ſo we come to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Words, and their plain and full import. <hi>viz.</hi> That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note</hi> 3. All <hi>they that Dye in the Lord are Bleſſed from henceforth;</hi> where we ſhall enquire and ſhew
<list>
                  <item>1. Who is meant here by <hi>the Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. What it is to <hi>Dye in the Lord,</hi> or who they are that may be ſaid ſo to dye.</item>
                  <item>3. Wherein they are <hi>bleſſed,</hi> or what and whence that bleſſedneſs is, that is aſſerted of them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:34925:23"/>4. What is the meaning of that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional word, <hi>henceforth,</hi> and what it may import.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>the Lord</hi> here is without all doubt meant Jeſus Chriſt, for He is <hi>Lord of All, Acts</hi> 10.36. for though there are that are called Lords, many, <hi>yet to us</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>there is but one Lord, Jeſus Chriſt by whom are all things and we by him,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. and we find like phraſes as this, expreſly mention him, as He in whom the believers on him dye; thus in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.18. <hi>they are fallen aſleep in Christ.</hi> And in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14.16. <hi>Them that ſleep is Jeſus will God bring with him, and the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt.</hi> He then is here meant by <hi>the Lord,</hi> yet not ſo as to exclude but include the Father and Holy Spirit, who are in and upon him; and He may well be ſtiled <hi>the Lord:</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As God, <hi>the Word with God in the beginning who was God,</hi> ſo <hi>all things were made by him,</hi> and He was and is by that right and ſtile as one with the Father (who made all things by him) and with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit (by whom or which he gave them their Formes, Virtues, and Beings) <hi>the Lord of All, Joh.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:34925:23"/>2. As man alſo taken into unity of perſon with the eternal word he muſt needs be, and ſo was and is Lord; the Manhood by that aſſumption into that perſonal union being advanced into intereſt in and communion with him in that his Dignity and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And ſo the Angel that came to declare to the Shepherds his Nativity called him, while he lay in the Manger, <hi>Chriſt the Lord, Luke</hi> 2.10.11. ſo the Evangeliſts ſpeak of him too in his ſtate of Miniſtery and ſervice very often, as <hi>the Lord appointed ſeventy, Luke</hi> 10.1. the Apoſtles ſaid unto the Lord, <hi>Lord incraſe our Faith, Luke</hi> 17.5. and himſelf bid the man out of whom he caſt a Legion of Devils, <hi>Go and ſhew how great things the Lord hath done for thee. Mark.</hi> 5.19. yea, and even in his dead ſtate as to his Body, the Angels ſent to declare his Reſurrection, call him Lord, as to his Body laid in the Sepulchre, ſaying, <hi>Come ſee the place where the Lord lay, Matth.</hi> 28.6. But eſpecially,</p>
            <p n="3">3. As Mediatour and <hi>Immanuel</hi> in his exalted and glorified ſtate, he is made of God the Father, and ſo declared to be Lord and Chriſt, as the fruit and reward of his Obedience and Sufferings to Death, <hi>the Death of the Croſs.</hi> And as to his actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al poſſeſſing in the nature of Man the Throne
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34925:24"/>
of Majeſty, and having thereon all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power inſtated on and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by him.</p>
            <p>To this end Chriſt both Dyed, Roſe and revived (or lived again) <hi>that he might be Lord of</hi> (or as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignifieth that he might Lord it, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Dominion over) <hi>the quick and dead, Rom.</hi> 14.9. and becauſe <hi>he humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and became obedient to the Death, the death of the Croſs, for this cauſe God hath highly exalted him and given him a Name above every name, That at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bowe both of things in heaven, and things in earth, and things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth: and that every tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is the Lord to the glory of God the Father, Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10, 11. who hath put all things under his feet, and made Angels, Authorities and Powers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto him. Yea indeed, over men he is worthily Lord by way of Purchaſe and right of Redemption, <hi>having given himſelf a Ranſome for all,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.6. whence the <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> are charged with <hi>denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>And he dyed</hi> (it's ſaid) <hi>for all that they</hi> (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be of mankind) <hi>that live ſhould not henceforth live to themſelves, but unto him who dyed for them and roſe again,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:34925:24"/>
5.15. Live to him, namely, as Servants to their proper Lord to whom they muſt give an account for all things. He is Lord over the Devils and evil Spirits by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, having Conquered and overcome them, ſpoiled them and led them Captive in Triumph, and ſo hath power to do his pleaſure with them, <hi>Col</hi> 2.15. And the good Angels willingly ſubmit themſelves to him as given to him of God with all other things in Heaven, Earth, under the earth, and in the Seas; and as to one whom God hath exalted to be over them, and bids to Worſhip him; yea, and they judge him moſt worthy of this Power and Dignity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his unparalleld acts for us and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over Death, and Hell, and Devils by his Death and Sufferings, <hi>aſcribing bleſſing, honour, glory and power to him, Heb.</hi> 1.6. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.11.12, 13. He then is <hi>the Lord</hi> in whom whoſoever <hi>dieth is bleſſed</hi> But</p>
            <p n="2">2. What's that <hi>dying in the Lord!</hi> For it is implyed here that ſome do <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> and that there is a <hi>dying in the Lord.</hi> But what's that! Indeed we may ſay in a ſenſe there is a dying in the Lord, and in a ſenſe there is no dying in him. In this ſenſe there is no dying in Chriſt, that is, He is not the Subject of this Dying; as in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34925:25"/>
Chriſt, and in him, ſometimes ſignifie in him as the ſubject of the thing ſpoken of, as when it is ſaid, <hi>in him we are Compleat, Col.</hi> 2.10. <hi>in him is no ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.5. in this ſenſe there is no Death or dying in him. He once dyed for ſin, the juſt for us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, <hi>but he dyeth no more, Death hath no more dominion over him, Rom.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>He was dead but is alive, and lives for evermore, Amen, Rev.</hi> 1.18. The ſong of the Saints is and ſhall be (as our Deceaſed friend and Siſter on her Death-bed noted) <hi>Worthy is the Lamb</hi> (not that is, but) <hi>that was ſlain to open the Book,</hi> &amp;c. He now is neither dying nor dead, <hi>Rev</hi> 5.9. it is true the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaid, <hi>they bare about in their body the dying of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.10. but that's to be underſtood either of the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings occaſioned by the conſtraining operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his love in dying for them believed by them, the dying that Chriſts love led them to endure for him and his Names ſake, and that to be the ſenſe, the next words may argue, in which he ſaith, <hi>We that live are alway delivered unto Death for Jeſus ſake, verſ.</hi> 11. ſo as the dying of Jeſus is the dying for Jeſus ſake; or elſe the dying of Jeſus is the dying of thoſe that are his Members, what is done to them being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him as done to himſelf, as is ſaid
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34925:25"/>
               <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.45. <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.4. But otherwiſe he dies not, in himſelf he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, nor may any ſuch thing be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be here implyed where the ſpeech is of others dying in him; concerning whom alſo neither may we underſtand that they dye in him as to their ſtate in him, or ſo as in the things which are properly of him, as ſuch a like Phraſe ſometimes ſignifies, as when it is ſaid, <hi>Ye are light in the Lord; that is,</hi> in what ye have in him, in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or in what ye have derived from him, and have or are after him as found in him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>and ye are wiſe in Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10. they that dye in him in ſuch a ſenſe are not bleſſed, but wretched; if any dye as to what they are in him, or derive from him; ſuch as Crucifie Chriſt again to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and that dye as to their dependance on him; Faith, Hope, and Rejoycing in him, or the like. Nor can it be ſaid that men dye by or as coming unto or into him, or being in him as to their ſtate God-ward, and in their ſpirits; but men live in and by him. He conveys not Death but Life unto men in their coming to and being in him; as is ſaid, <hi>In the way of righteouſneſs is Life, and in the path way thereof there is no Death,</hi> Prov. 12.28. <hi>Death,</hi> as it is <hi>the wages of ſin,</hi> though ſuffered and ſuſtained
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34925:26"/>
by Chriſt, yet it is not met with in and from Chriſt as a proper conſequent of him or of Faith in him, but Life: <hi>He that hath the Son hath life,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.12. <hi>who dyed that we might live in and by him,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.9, 10. And yet there is a <hi>dying in the Lord,</hi> that is, of thoſe that are in the Lord, and that in the view and beholding of him as the effect or operation of him beheld and believed on. As to ſay,</p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Dying</hi> to our Selves, the World, and Sin; a letting go our Confidence, rejoycing in, or reſting on our own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, righteouſneſs, the fleſh or fleſhly priviledges, and expectations of life from our keeping of or conformity to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or the like; as in this ſenſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>I through the law am dead to the law that I may live to God: I am crucifyed with Chriſt, yet I live, not I, but Chriſt liveth in me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19, 20, <hi>and ye brethren, are dead to the law by the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt,</hi> namely by it as Crucified for you, believed in by you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. and ſo <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory in any thing ſave in the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by which the World is crucified to me and I to the World,</hi> Gal. 6.14. <hi>and what things were advantage to me thoſe I counted loſs for Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 3.7. <hi>and reckon your
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34925:26"/>
ſelves dead to ſin,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. And this kind of Dying may be taken in here incluſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as that that foreruns and makes way for this <hi>dying in the Lord,</hi> and they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that in ſuch ſenſe Dye in or through the Lord, or the knowledge of him: <hi>For if we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>But that which is properly meant here is, that thoſe that are in Chriſt may dye as to the bodily death, the being in Chriſt and the Bodily death are conſiſtent; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Dying and bleſſedneſs could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt together, as we ſhewed they do: for there is no bleſſedneſs out of Chriſt. And that a bodily in Chriſt may ſtand together with bodily death is further clear, in that as Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e not to prevent and keep men from bodily death by his dying, but to obtain a reſurrection out of it; ſo neither doth men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing in Chriſt prevent or annull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the deriving life from Chriſt is not ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deriving life as puts by the Body from dying: For it is not derived upon the Body, but from (and ſo after) its Death. <hi>It is appointed for men once to Dye,</hi> and that appointment was made after the promiſe of Chriſt and of his defeating the Devils Plot, the <hi>bruiſing his head,</hi> and therefore is conſiſtent with it. Chriſt can
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34925:27"/>
can and will defeat Sathans plot for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man out everlaſtingly from God though they dye as to the Body, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. with <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15, 16. Chriſt indeed being belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on, gives forth his divine Spirit and life for quickening our ſpirit and expelling Death out of that, raiſing it up to a lively hope in God; but it expels not Death out of the body till the Reſurrection of the dead. <hi>The body is ſtill dead</hi> (under the Sentence of and in the way to Death) <hi>becauſe of ſin</hi> (that yet remains in it) <hi>but the Spirit or inward man, is life for righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 8.10. thence, <hi>we ſee wiſe men dye, Pſal.</hi> 49.11. and as was mentioned before, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> is dead, and <hi>Moſes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are dead, in reſpect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outward man; though they were brought into and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and abode in Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fare alſo. And this God orders for divers good cauſes, as I have ſhewed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Balaams wiſh,</hi> as to keep us always lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and humble in our ſelves; and dependan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on God and mindful of our latter end; and ſo more heedful to the inſtructions of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and that God and Chriſt might be glorified in raiſing us up from the Dead.</p>
            <p>But now to <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> in this ſenſe ſignifies and hath in it,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34925:27"/>1. A continuance in Chriſt, even in the Faith and Obedience of him till Death and in Death, ſo as that we lay down our lives or give up our breath, holding faſt the Faith and grace of Chriſt, as it is ſaid of the Patriarchs, <hi>that they all dyed in the Faith,</hi> ſo as retaining and not going out from the Faith; when their ſpirits left and went out of their bodies, yet they went not out from Chriſt, from believing and hoping in him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. And there may be further in it</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſpending and laying down the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily life in an exerciſe of Faith and Hope in Chriſt and walking in the Spirit, vertues and ſervice of Chriſt, ſo as that the dying is in a ſenſe the effect and product to the Fleſh of believing and walking in him, as the Apoſtles that ſo walked in Chriſt, as that they ſpent themſelves, and ſtrength, and life as it were in the flames of his love to them, and zeal for him thence ſpringing, being offered up as a Sacrifice as it were, <hi>upon the ſacrifice and ſervice of the Faith,</hi> Phil. 2.17. <hi>offered</hi> (or pouered out as a drink-offering, as the word ſignifies) in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. and in ſome caſes and times (as thoſe before mentioned under the cruelties of the Beaſt and falſe Prophet) it takes in</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Dying in the Cauſe of Chriſt, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34925:28"/>
for his ſake as Martyrs put to Death for <hi>bearing witneſs and teſtimony to him, as thoſe beheaded for the witneſs of Chriſt, and the Word of God, and for not worſhipping the Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9. and 20.4. We may put them together and ſay, that when men are, and continue in the Faith of Chriſt, and ſo in the love and vertues of Chriſt too, and <hi>in death, Rev.</hi> 2.10 and by the force of that they have in and from Chriſt, lay down or ſpend out their lives either in ſerving, or ſuffering for Chriſt; then may they be ſaid to <hi>dye in the Lord:</hi> and all that ſo dye, <hi>dye in the Lord.</hi> But yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they that in any ſuch ſenſe <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> may be ſaid alſo in another ſenſe (which pertains to, and is the immediate ſpring of their bleſſedneſs) to dye in him. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In the love of the Lord; as being the objects of his favourable acceptance, and ſo encloſed as it were in his arms: in his vertues as being encompaſſed about with the vertues of his Sufferings and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and ſo in his Covenant and Promiſes; and thence <hi>They,</hi> all they that ſo Dye, in what way ſoever, as to the outward way of dying they dye: whether by a fair Death on their Beds, or by any violent Death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them, whether by a more eaſie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34925:28"/>
or more ſharp and painful death; yea, though they dye of Poverty, or are full of Sores, as <hi>Lazarus,</hi> yet they are Bleſſed; though in the ſight of men they ſeem moſt miſerable, yet they are in a happy ſtate and condition. Which we are nextly</p>
            <p n="3">3. To enquire into, and ſhew what that Bleſſedeeſs is, and how they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; we may ſay, Bleſſedneſs ſtands in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption or freedom from what's evil and harmful: and in having intereſt in and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of good to content and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and they that <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> are in ſuch a ſtate even while dead; and needs they muſt be ſo. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Chriſt there is all that may free, exempt or deliver a man from evil; and there is all that may do good, and make content and ſatisfied, and ſo all that may make one both privatively and poſitively Bleſſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In him is freedom and deliverance from evil not onely for himſelf, but ſo as it may be for the freeing of others, not onely ſin hath no dominion over, or place in him (though he was made ſin, and bare our ſins for us, yet having dyed for it, and being raiſed again, in him is no ſin, no ſin now, on, or imputed to him) but alſo there is freedom from it for us, forgiveneſs of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34925:29"/>
it, and juſtification from it as is ſaid. <hi>Be it known to you that in this man is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you forgiveneſs of ſins,</hi> Acts 13.38. And, <hi>there is forgiveneſs with thee that thou mayeſt be feared,</hi> Pſal. 130.4. yea, and not onely is he clean from it, but with him is cleanſing too; He hath made a <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of our ſins,</hi> Heb. 1.3. <hi>opened a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for</hi> waſhing and <hi>cleanſing</hi> us, <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. and in both reſpects he is the Saviour from ſin, both as to the imputation, and as to the pollution of it. And where ſin is taken away, or removed, evil of Wrath and Puniſhment hath no place. While ſin was imputed to, and laid upon Chriſt, he was alſo obnoxious to the curſe, and wrath, that was the Wages of it: And while God imputes ſin, and it is not waſhed off a man, puniſhment, and evil of wrath may befal him; but as in him there is forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of, and cleanſing from ſin, ſo in him is deliverance from wrath too, either as to miſery inflicted on the Creature, or as to the hiding of Gods face, or withdrawing his favour from it, <hi>being juſtified from his Blood,</hi> how much more ſaved <hi>from wrath!</hi> both Poſitive and Privative; Poſitive of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and Privative of good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. and then, as there is none hath power over him in the leaſt, ſo in him there is that infinite
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34925:29"/>
wiſdome and power, by which he is All ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſave us from them; and order their enmities as he ſees good: ſo as he can ſuffer them to act forth their malice, and yet ſecure thoſe againſt whom it's act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo as it ſhall have no evil influence upon them; yea, all enemies ſpiritual and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral are at his beck and will, to do to, or with them as he pleaſes, and he can let out or reſtrain their wrath; inflict puniſhments by them, or ſave from, or deliver out of the troubles they occaſion, as he pleaſes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In him alſo is all fulneſs of good wherewith he may do us good, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and ſatisfie us; <hi>for all the fulneſs of the God-head dwells bodily in him, and in him we are compleat,</hi> Col. 2.9, 10. It hath pleaſed all fulneſs to (or it hath pleaſed the Father, that all Fulneſs ſhould) <hi>dwell in him, Col</hi> 1.19. the Father is in him, with all the fulneſs of his love and favour, He is enough to ſatisfie the Soul for ever, and produce any good to it that he pleaſes. In him is the fulneſs of the holy Spirit, and of all his glorious Power, Wiſdom, Love, Sweetneſs and Comfort; and with all its moſt enabling and enriching vertues, ſo as he can <hi>baptiſe with it,</hi> us, and <hi>whom he pleaſeth, Iſa.</hi> 42.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34925:30"/>
and 7.37, 38, 39. His are all Riches and precious treaſures; all things in Heaven and Earth are his, Riches and Honour are with him, yea, <hi>durable Riches and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> his <hi>Fruit is better then gold, yea then fine gold, and his revenue better then choice ſilver,</hi> Prov. 8.18, 19. <hi>Length of days are in his right hand</hi> (even Immortality and Eternal Life) <hi>and in his left hand Riches and Honour. His ways are ways of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs and all his paths are peace. He is a tree of life to them that lay hold on him, and happy therefore is every one that retains him, Prov.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17, 18. Happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, For</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whoſoever comes into him, is, and abides in him, is intereſted in all that is his, and that is in him and comes to the participation of the benefit thereof; they that are made in him through the grace of God, to them he is made of God, <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Righteouſneſs, Holineſs and Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. They have him to be theirs, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.12. yea, and in him they have the Father alſo, being and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Son, they are in the Father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2 24. <hi>In God the Father and in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. &amp; 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. and as they are both in Father, and Son, <hi>ſo they have both,</hi> 2 Joh. 9. And how can
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34925:30"/>
they that have ſuch a portion and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but be happy?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Privatively Happy, ſo as to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from all that is evil; from ſin, the Root of all evil, ſo it is not imputed to to them, <hi>In him all that believe are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from all things which they could not be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the law of Moſes,</hi> Acts 13.9. <hi>in him we have redemption through his Blood the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of ſins,</hi> Eph. 1.7. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14 ſo as to be ſanctified &amp; cleanſed from ſin, ſo as <hi>it ſhall not have dominion over thoſe that believe in</hi> (and ſo are, and abide in him) <hi>Rom</hi> 6.14. <hi>He that abideth in him ſinneth not,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.6. and then <hi>there is no Condemnation to them that are in him, that walk not after the Fleſh but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1. And ſo there is no evil in their Portion, <hi>there ſhall no evil happen to the juſt,</hi> as they are that are in, and abide in Chriſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.21. <hi>All things work together for good to them,</hi> Rom. 8.28. and ſo there is no Death to them, nothing of miſery, or ſeparation from God, which is the death of the Soul, nothing of deſtruction, <hi>they ſhall not periſh,</hi> Joh. 3.16.</p>
            <p>True it is, that they may have, and actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have Enemies againſt them, within, and without; but Chriſt is to them a place of ſure Defence againſt them, and preſerves
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34925:31"/>
their Souls; <hi>Their place of defence is on high, a place of the munition of rocks, Iſa.</hi> 33.16. and they dwell ſafely, ſo as they may be alſo quiet from the fear of evil, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.33. being and dwelling in him who is the moſt High, and in his ſecret place they dwell, under the ſhadow and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Almighty, ſaying of him, <hi>Who is the Lord? He is my rock and my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, my God in whom I will trust,</hi> ſurely <hi>He will deliver them from the ſnare of the Fowler, and from the truly noiſome Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. He will cover them with his feathers, and under his wings ſhall they truſt, his truth ſhall be their ſhield and buckler, ſo as they ſhall not be afraid of the terrour by night, nor of the arrow that flyeth by day.</hi> Yea dwelling in the Lord, as in their refuge, and having him, the moſt High, for their habitation there ſhall no evil befal them, nor any Plague come nigh their dwelling, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 9, 10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Poſitively happy, in the enjoyment of, and intereſt (at leaſt) in all that's good for as <hi>the Lord is a ſtrong houſe or houſe of defence to them that are in him,</hi> Pſal. 31.2. and 71.3, ſo he is alſo to them <hi>a houſe of feaſting or ſacrifices,</hi> Prov. 9.1, 2, 3. and <hi>they that truſt in him and under the ſhadow of his wings ſhall abundantly be ſatisfied with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34925:31"/>
the fatneſs of his houſe;</hi> and <hi>he will make them drink of the rivers of his pleaſures,</hi> Pſal. 36.7, 8, 9. He is to them <hi>a fountain of life and living waters, both quickning, purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſatisfing them.</hi> He is to them <hi>a ſun; and ſhield, and will give them grace and glory and no good thing will he withhold from them that are upright with him,</hi> Pſal. 84.11. in him they have, and from him derive that heavenly wiſdom, that brings with it to them, Riches, and Honour, and Life, in him they have, and from him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that holy Spirit whoſe fruit is Love, Joy, Peace, and in a word, all Goodneſs; Righteouſneſs and Truth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Joh</hi> 7.38, 39. and 4.14. <hi>Ephſ.</hi> 5 8. yea, in him they have the Adoption of Sons, and are honoured with that near relation to God, where through they become his Heirs <hi>joynt-heirs with Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 8.17. And if the Lord being their <hi>ſhepherd they ſhall not want,</hi> Pſal. 23.1. How ſhall they want then, God being their Father, Chriſt their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they joynt-heirs with him? theſe are the fearers of the Lord that are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the very fear of the Lord is ſuch a Bleſſing to them as tendeth to life, ſo as they ſhall abide ſatisfied with it, <hi>and ſhall not be viſited of evil,</hi> Pſal. 112.1. Prov. 19.23. Well may it be ſaid of every ſuch
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34925:32"/>
one, as is ſaid of <hi>Aſher,</hi> whoſe name ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified Bleſſed, <hi>that his bread or portion is fat,</hi> Gen. 49.20. or as of <hi>Nepthali,</hi> that he is, and ſhall be <hi>ſatisfied with favour,</hi> Deut. 33.23. and of them all as is ſaid of <hi>Iſrael, Happy art thou, O Iſrael, ſaved by the Lord, the Eternal God is thy refuge, or manſions, and underneath thee</hi> (even when thou falleſt loweſt) <hi>are the everlaſting arms, who is like unto thee! who haſt the Lord for the ſhield of thy help and whoſe ſword is thy excellency,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 33.17.29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If it be ſaid, This is indeed the portion of them that are in Chirſt, while alive here: but here we are to speak of thoſe that are Dead dying in Chriſt; <hi>I anſwer:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This is the Portion of men in Chriſt at all times, whether alive or dead, as to the Body or Fleſh; yea, it's rather their Portion that Dye in Chriſt, then of others; for if men be in Chriſt when they live here, and before they dye turn out from him, and ſo dye not in him, they looſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit all this Bleſſedneſs; for Bleſſedneſs is ſo the Portion of Chriſt (who onely hath purchaſed and obtained it into himſelf by his onely perfect, and moſt acceptable righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34925:32"/>
that though he have it not for himſelf onely, but for us, yet there is no intereſt in it, nor enjoyment of it to be had out of, or apart from him; that being alſo true, that <hi>he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. He therefore that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth and abideth not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, hath not God, and ſo not life; for God there anſwers to Father and Son in the next Clauſe, which Son is the life, and hath the life given of God to us in himſelf, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by Faith; but if</hi> (he or) <hi>any man draw back my Soul ſhall have no pleaſure in him:</hi> Nay he that draws back, <hi>draws back to perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Heb. 37.38, 39. ſo as to looſe all this Portion, and his Soul in the loſs of it. But while any man is in Chriſt alive or dead, he is in a full and moſt accompliſht treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all bliſs and happineſs; and in the diſpoſe and favour of one perfectly Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to communicate and give forth of his fulneſs according to his Promiſes; all the Promiſes of God are in him; yea, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> And he that is in him, is in him an heir of them, and abiding in him, ſhall not fail to inherit them, though they as to the body dye, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Gal</hi> 3.29.: For</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34925:33"/>2. Death, this bodily death, doth not make any alteration as to mens being in him, it is not the going of the Soul out of the Body, that is, its going out of Chriſt, they that <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> are in the Lord in the time and act of his dying, laying down their lives, or breathing out their Spirits in the Faith and in the Spirit of him; they are yet in him incloſed in his Arms, in his favour, and love, and Covenant with him, whence he is ſtill, even in Death, as we noted before, ſtiled their God, for though Dead men, and as to bodily life, yet they live to him, and in reſpect of their ſpirits ſee no Death, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.51. <hi>their hearts ſhall live for ever,</hi> Pſal. 22.26. this Death is called a ſleep; <hi>they that ſleep in Jeſus ſhall God bring with him,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.14. And as the bodily ſleep makes no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in relation or Covenant-engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: no more doth the bodily Death in relation to God and Chriſt, and intereſt in the Covenant and Promiſes of his bleſſing; a Child is the Fathers Child as well when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep as when awake, and is nevertheleſs an Heir to an Eſtate given by deed of gift, or by the Fathers Will and Teſtament. Nor is a Wife the leſs the Wife, and in the marriage-covenant when ſhe lies faſt aſleep in her Husbands boſom, then when ſhe is moſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34925:33"/>
awake and active; and therefore is in as happy a condition (if happy in her Marriage) then, as at other times; yea, we may ſay of the man aſleep in Chriſt, or (which is all one) Dead in the Lord, that his ſtate is better then before, as we ſhall ſhew God willing, in what follows; for as <hi>the Dead that dye in the Lord</hi> are bleſſed both privatively as they are exempted from, &amp; ſecured againſt evil: and poſitively, as they are intereſted in Chriſt, &amp; in all, the good that is in him, and to be communicated by him: So alſo they are</p>
            <p n="3">3. Comparatively Bleſſed, more bleſſed in divers reſpects then divers others, or then themſelves in former times.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Comparatively to other men they be happy, whether they be</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe that Dye, and are dead out of the Lord, they are happy in reſpect of them howſoever they dye; it may be in the appearance of men ſinners that dye in their ſins are happier in their Death then they, <hi>as having no bands in their death,</hi> as is ſaid, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.4 they may lye and dye in ſtately Rooms, and ſoft Beds, encompaſſed about with their Friends and Kindred, feel little pain, diſpoſe of great eſtates to their Children &amp; friends; they may poſſibly expreſs no fear of Hell, but hope they ſhall go to heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22, 23. They may, when dead, have coſtly Funerals, &amp; ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34925:34"/>
Monuments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as thoſe that dye in Chriſt may dye grievous Deaths in the ſight of men, of ſharp Diſeaſes, full of Sores and Boyles, in Priſons, Dungeons, yea, on Racks or Gibbets, as it is ſaid of thoſe Saints of whom the world was not worthy; that they were ſome Tortured, others Stoned, others Sawn aſunder, others ſlain with the Sword; that they were deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute (of ſuccour, namely, Friends, means of helpfulneſs, and the like) Afflicted, Torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37, 38. and yet for all this great difference, as to the way and outward manner of Dying; Yea, though we add alſo, that they being tempted may cry out, as forſaken of God (as our Lord Jeſus on the Croſs) yet theſe that dye in the Lord are infinitely Bleſſed above the other; nay, rather, Bleſſed, and not at all the other, let them dye as deſirably otherwiſe they can, yea, though alſo they, when Dead, have their Names cryed up of men, as if they were Worthy, Gallant, Honourable perſons; and thoſe that <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> be accounted (as our Lord was by the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.62, 63) <hi>as Deceivers;</hi> or (as the Papiſts called divers of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> martyrs) ſtinking martyrs, mad men, Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet theſe latter, <hi>they that dye in the Lord,</hi> are far happier then the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34925:34"/>We may compare thoſe two men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>Luke</hi> 16.19. the <hi>Rich man</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> they both dyed. But oh how great a difference to appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in their dying! the one in a Rich ſtate, and therefore no doubt but had or might have Friends, and Phyſicians about him, and want no Attendance; and after Death had a Burial; which we find not ſaid of the poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he might dye of his Sores, and in ſome ditch, and his body might be expoſed to the Birds or Beaſts of prey (as thoſe Saints mentioned in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.2, 3, 4.) But yet the differerce in the goodneſs of their ſtate when dead, was far more for the advantage on <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſide, then the goodneſs of the way of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dying was on the Rich man's ſide: For after Death the poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> was carried of Angels into <hi>Abraham's</hi> boſome, and was comforted and refreſhed with everlaſting Conſolations, not to be loſt again: When the Rich man was in Hell, tormented without eaſe, or end; not having either poſſibility of eſcape from thence, or of enjoying there ſo much as one drop of Water to cool the tip of his tongue. Who would chooſe to dye as the Rich man, with ſuch a ſtate after death, rather then as the poor man, or any of the moſt cruelly Martyred
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34925:35"/>
good man, having the poor man's after-ſtate? who would not rather go through any difficult and dirty way from a Priſon, to a Throne, then to ſlide down from ſome ſtately, Throne, or off ſome pleaſant Hill beſtrawed with ſweeteſt Flowers in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent; or attended alſo with the moſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious Muſick into a dark Dungeon, to lie and rot there in the midſt of noiſome ſtenches, pinch'd and pin'd away with Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or made a prey to venemous Snakes and Serpents. <hi>The righteous hath hope his Death, but the wicked is driven away in his wickedneſs,</hi> Prov. 14.32. and <hi>the hope of the Hypocrite ſhall periſh, and be as the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up of the ghoſt,</hi> Job 18.13, 14. and 11.20. but <hi>the hope of the righteous ſhall be gladneſs,</hi> Prov. 10.28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that live in the greateſt pomp and ſplendor in the world, injoying the greateſt fulneſs of Riches, Honour, and Glory; or the moſt delightful continuing pleaſures, for theſe in the midſt of their enjoyments are in a ſtate of incertainty. Their Riches are uncertain riches, they may take them wings and fly away, the Thief may ſteal them, or the Moth and ruſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them: Their Honours like <hi>Hamans</hi> may end upon a Gallows, or as <hi>Ahithophels</hi> in a Halter; and all their pleaſures in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34925:35"/>
vaniſh, and they may come with <hi>Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the <hi>Lydian</hi> King, to learn the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of all things here by ſad Experience, falling into the hand and Power of their Enemies; The pleaſures of ſin are but for a ſeaſon, and the reproches of Chriſt are far greater Riches, than all <hi>the treaſures of Egypt,</hi> or of the World, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25, 26. The Wealthieſt and moſt Honoured perſons here muſt dye, and then <hi>they ſhall carry nothing away with them, nor their pomp and glory deſcend after them,</hi> Pſal. 49.17. though while they live they bleſs their ſouls and men praiſe them as doing well for themſelves; yet when Death comes, then all their felicity in theſe enjoyments vaniſh like pleaſant dreams when one awaketh, and ing out of Chriſt, <hi>they go to the generation of their Fathers, and ſhall never ſee light,</hi> Pſal. 49.18, 19. yea, then how are they brought into deſolation as in a moment, <hi>and utterly conſumed with terrours,</hi> Pſal. 73.19. then begin their miſeries never to end, when the miſeries of the others, and all their griefs and ſorrows are at an end, never more to return, and then end the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings Joys for ever; when the dead in Chriſt have more increaſe of Joy, or enter into thoſe Joys that never ſhall end. And though it's true, that the proſperous ſinner
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34925:36"/>
living yet at eaſe and in fulneſs, is in a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Repentance, and ſo in a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtate, then he that dyes in his ſins, and is dead out of Chriſt: Yet conſidering what ſnares there are in ſuch injoyments, and how hard it is for a Rich man to enter into Gods Kingdom, and how uſually the proſperity of fools (that is, evil men, for all ſuch are very fools in Gods reckoning, whoſe judgment is according to truth) deſtroy them; that they are perſons ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing high, but in ſlippery places, and are in very great danger of being every hour caſt from their heigth into deſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.18. and conſidering on the other hand, that the man dead in Chriſt, is out of all danger of any miſcarriage, in preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion in their ſpirits, of that preſence of Chriſt, where is that fulneſs of Joy which infinitely tranſcends all the injoyments of this world how great ſoever, and that they are ſure, and certain of Eternal Happineſs for ever; their ſtate muſt needs be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded infinitely better then the others. Yea, on that account alſo <hi>Bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Comparatively to themſelves, while living in the world, more bleſſed now, than then, as the Apoſtle implies when he ſaith, that though living in the Fleſh, he had this fruit of his labour, that he lived to Chriſt,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34925:36"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> to the magnifying of him: Yet he had a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt as a thing to him far better, <hi>Phil.</hi> 122, 23. for now they are abſolutely bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy though not yet fully and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatively in the higheſt and greateſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Happineſs and Glory; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body muſt be waited for, for that when Body and Soul reunited, ſhall be glorified, and all the Saints compleatly brought together, ſhall receive the full of the Glory promiſed, and have to each ones particular injoyment the acceſſion of the glory of all the reſt with them.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Cicero</hi> an Heathen Orator, could fancy a wonderful Happineſs in the deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Moraliſts, enjoying the fellowſhip of each others Souls <note n="*" place="margin">O proeclarum illum diem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſo as to cry out,
<q>O that gallant day! When ſhall I go to the Council and Company of Souls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
What may the Chriſtian judge of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and aſſured Society of happy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and raiſed perſons, together with Chriſt for ever? But now they are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> their happineſs hangs no
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34925:37"/>
longer upon any Condition that may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fail in, as before it did upon an <hi>If ye continue.</hi> And though that <hi>If</hi> was of no great burthen ſo as to imply ſo much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as to fill them with diſquieting fears to hinder their rejoycing in aſſured hope, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many ingagements to abide, and ſo great incouragements in Chriſt to truſt in him for his delivering them from all evil, &amp; preſerving them to his heavenly kingdom: Yet there is both a poſſibility yet remaining, of their ſailing, and other Conſiderations alſo; as of their poſſibility and danger of ſinning and diſhonouring Chriſt, their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expoſed to griefs, pains, temptations, and the like; from which they ſhall then be for ever freed, that add a Preheminence to the ſtate of their Death, as alſo that they ſhall be ſo <hi>at home with the Lord,</hi> as before they were not, nor could be; as is implied 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23. indeed as to uſefulneſs to others they are not in ſo good a ſtate, <hi>they periſh from among the Children of men,</hi> Pſal. 12.1 Iſa. 57.1. They have no more opportunity of doing good to, or receiving good from them; they they are as to that, in a place and ſtate of ſilence, whence its wiſdom to be doing good to all while alive, and we have thereto opportunity, and to let our hand do what is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34925:37"/>
finds to do with all our diligence to that purpoſe, becauſe in the Grave whither we go, there is no Work which we can doe, nor nothing we can deviſe for them, as for that cauſe, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was in a ſtrait, and knew not whether to chooſe Death or Life, becauſe for him to continue in the Fleſh would be better for his Brethren, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.22, 24. but yet in reſpect of the Saints ſtate of freedom from evils both of Sin and Suffering and enjoyment of the Lord, they are much better then in the ſtate of this Life; as much better, as it's better for a poor Pilgrim and Forreiner expoſed to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of vexations and hazzards, to be at home in his own Countrey, &amp; in ſome ſafe &amp; quiet poſſeſſion of a ſettled comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or for a poor toſſed weather-beaten Seaman to be ſafely harboured in the Port he is bound for; and that may be alſo one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the addition of the other word <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth.</hi> And ſo we come to the next Inquiry,</p>
            <p n="4">4. What is this <hi>Henceforth?</hi> or why is that added? Were they not bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Surely yes, <hi>Ye are the Bleſſed of the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Holy Ghoſt to perſons yet or then alive, that feared the Lord) <hi>you, and your Children,</hi> Pſal. 115.13, 15. and <hi>bleſſed is the man</hi> (whether alive or dead as to the body) <hi>that truſteth in the Lord or that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34925:38"/>
keepeth his Commandments,</hi> Pſal. 34.8. and 112.1. But this word <hi>Henceforth,</hi> may be two ways referred, as was ſignified before; namely, either</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the word <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> the thing aſſerted of thoſe that <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> as if they that dye at any time in the Lord are thenceforth Bleſſed, even from the time of their Death, and then it is not ſaid ſo to imply, they were not in a bleſſed way before, or in the way to Bleſſedneſs; But to imply that bleſſedneſs may rather, or more properly from that time be ſtiled theirs, as more actually and abſolutely the ſubjects of it, they were rather but in the way to it before then injoyers of it, though being upright and perfect in the way they had the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God with and upon them, and were bleſſed therein; but yet, as we ſaid before, there was an <hi>If</hi> upon them, <hi>If they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to the end,</hi> Col. 1.23. <hi>If ye continue in the Faith grounded and ſettled, and not be moved away from the hope of the Gospel. He that endures to the end ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Matth. 24.13. <hi>be thou faithful to the death, and I will give thee a crown of life,</hi> Rev. 2.10. but <hi>if the righteous man</hi> (how long ſoever he hath been righteous, and how near ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever to the prize he be come) <hi>turn from his righteouſneſs and commit iniquity he ſhall dye.</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34925:38"/>
Ezek. 33.13, 18. There were ſome of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that held out till they were cloſe by the borders of <hi>Canaan,</hi> till the Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth year of their March, and till they had ſeen the Conqueſt over the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and yet then committing Fornication with the Daughters of <hi>Moab,</hi> and eating the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Dead, they periſhed and went not over <hi>Jordan;</hi> To admoniſh us, that though there is no fear or danger to the diligent and circumſpect; yet it's dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous at any time to grow remiſs becauſe a poſſibility at any time of a miſcarriage till the field be wonne, the warfare be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. And therefore our Saviour ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>Take heed leaſt at any time</hi> (how near ſoever you be come to the Gaol) <hi>your hearts be overcharged with ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, and cares of this life, and that day come upon you unawares, for as a ſnare ſhall it come upon all thoſe that dwell upon the face of the earth, watch ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and pray always, that ye may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy to eſcape all theſe things, and to stand before the Son of man,</hi> Luke 21.34, 35, 36. Sometimes a Ship that hath eſcaped the dangers of the Sea, may through careleſneſs ſink and be loſt at the entrance into the Harbour; but when in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour then it's ſafe. It is ſo however here,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34925:39"/>
after Death there is no miſcarriage. <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, when ready to be offered up, and his departure was at hand) <hi>is laid up for me the crown of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, 2 Tim.</hi> 4.8. then their ſtate is fixed; no paſſing or falling from Paradiſe again; when that's attained, no going thence to the place of Torment, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. Yea, they are thenceforth not onely more abſolutely and aſſuredly bleſſed, but alſo, more fully as to attainment being then <hi>at home with Chriſt,</hi> as we ſaid before, from the time of their Death and before the Reſurrection. Though the fulneſs of their Bleſſedneſs is not till then, yet both a more full enjoyment is had from the time of their death then before (they go not to Purgatory then ſurely, for then after death their caſe would be ſadder then before) and alſo a certainty of the enjoyment of that fulneſs in the time thereof. It is laid up in a ſure and ſafe Cuſtody to be given forth by a moſt faithful and righteous hand, yea, the word there in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. rendred, <hi>laid up,</hi> is the ſame that's uſed of Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. and there tranſlated, <hi>Appointed,</hi> ſo as we may ſay, that it is not more certainly Decreed <hi>that men Dye once and come to Judgement,</hi> then it is,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34925:39"/>
that they who finiſh their Courſe in the Lord and <hi>keep the Faith,</hi> ſhall receive the full and final reward of the Crown of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Or elſe the word <hi>(Henceforth)</hi> may have a peculiar reſpect to the times before mentioned, and to the Subject <hi>thoſe that Dye in the Lord,</hi> with reference to the times in the rage of the Beaſt; when the greateſt exerciſe ſhall be of the Saints pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when their patience ſhall be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable patience indeed, and they that then abide will be eminently and to purpoſe keepers of Gods Commandments, and of the Faith of Jeſus; from that time <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord,</hi> not as if they that indeed Dye in the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore! were not Bleſſed, but to ſignifie ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great miſeries that will attend thoſe times through the oppreſſion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, that it will be a wonderful peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and calamitous time, ſo that it will be a great mercy to be well gone out of it, ſo as but to be and Dye in the Lord; yea, the ſooner the better, like that in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.13 where the Wiſeman conſidering the <hi>oppreſſions done under the Sun, and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the tears of the oppreſſed, and that they had no Comforter, that on the oppreſſours ſide is
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34925:40"/>
Power, but the oppreſſed have no Comforter;</hi> He praiſed <hi>the Dead that were already dead more then the living which were yet alive.</hi> This ſenſe of the words ſuits well alſo with that reading, or Tranſlation of the word that ſome judge the righter here, <hi>viz. that dye in the Lord speedily.</hi> And this may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be ſo, becauſe of what reſults from thoſe Calamities. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The great difficulty of holding faſt the Faith and profeſſion of it, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of falling from it that will then be, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>When the Son of man comes, ſhall he find faith on the earth?</hi> Luke 18.8. truely in a ſenſe, at other times men may <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> that is, in an external Profeſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him according to truth, crying, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> and yet not be bleſſed, not enter the Kingdom, being not indeed and heartily doers of Gods will; but it may be ſignified that <hi>Henceforth,</hi> from the time of the Beaſts ſore Rage, and the ſad Perſecutions thence enſuing, none ſhall be able to make a right profeſſion of the Faith, ſo as to perſevere to Death in it, but ſuch as be indeed Saints and perſons indued with ſingular patience, real and hearty keepers of Gods Commandments, and therefore all that dye in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34925:40"/>
of the Faith then really Bleſſed and Happy. Or elſe alſo,</p>
            <p n="3">3: To ſignifie a more eminent degree of Bleſſedneſs to be the portion of thoſe that then ſhall hold out ſo as to <hi>Dye in the Lord,</hi> a bleſſedneſs proportionable to that very ſad wo and miſery threatened to to the Beaſt-worſhippers, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9, 10, 11. after the Preaching of the Everlaſting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel and downfal of <hi>Babylon</hi> declared, as thoſe Beaſt-worſhippers <hi>ſhall drink of the wine of the Wrath of God, poured out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture into the Cup of his Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimstone in the preſence of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in the preſence of the Lamb, and the ſmoke of their torment aſcends up for ever and ever. And they have no reſt day nor night.</hi> A moſt dreadful Sentence, able to deter any one from Worſhipping him: On the other ſide here is a like excellent manner of Bleſſedneſs ſignified to be the portion of thoſe that <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> to allure the Servants of God, or any of the People to whom the Goſpel is Preached to the worſhip of God, and conſtancy to Chriſt, againſt the Beaſt; that they that <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> ſhall upon their Death be bleſſed with a witneſs, more abundantly bleſſed, as the word <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> ſometimes ſeems
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34925:41"/>
to ſignifie; as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. for as it's an aggravation of ſin when it is againſt light and warning, and brings the greater and ſeverer judgment; whereas <hi>the times of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God winks at,</hi> Acts 17.30, 31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 23; &amp; 10.20, 29. So it's an aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of Virtue to be good in the worſt of times, and to cleave to God and Chriſt againſt the greateſt diſcouragements and oppoſitions; and they that ſo do, ſhall receive the greater bleſſedneſs as their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>But we ſhall have occaſion to Conſider wherein they may be ſaid to be more chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed, in ſpeaking to the other part of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Confirmation of this truth aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which is twofold,
<list>
                  <item>1. By Authority.</item>
                  <item>2. By Argument and Evidence.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By Authority; The teſtimony of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Witneſſes is a good evidence of any matter of fact aſſerted, or of any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whereof they have ſufficient cogniſance. Now here we have the Authority and Teſtimony of one that is as good as, yea better then ten thouſand, even the Spirit, which is the Truth: <hi>Yea, ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:34925:41"/>By the Spirit, is meant the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of Truth; for He is Emphatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>The Spirit;</hi> and is divers times ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this Book, as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. and 3. He is ſo called ſeven times, <hi>viz.</hi> in the cloſe of every Epiſtle where it is ſaid, <hi>Let him that hath an ear hear what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi> And in Chap 22.17. <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come.</hi> And that he is a ſufficient Witneſs to any thing he Saith and Teſtifies to, is evident in that</p>
            <p n="1">1. He is perfect in underſtanding and knowledge, being <hi>the Spirit of Wiſdome, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Counſel and Knowledge,</hi> Iſa. 11.2. <hi>He that ſearcheth all things even the deep things of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore He cannot erre or miſtake. And then</p>
            <p n="2">2. He <hi>the Spirit of Truth,</hi> Joh. 14.16, 17. yea, The truth; and therefore it is He that <hi>beareth witneſs to Chriſt and the things of him,</hi> 1 Joh. 5, 6. therefore he neither will nor can lie; for he is one with the Father, and with the Son, one God. And God cannot lie, deceive or falſifie; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs and falſhood are an abomination to him and to his lips, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.7, 8. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one that hath an ear may well hear, as he is bid, what he ſaith. And
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34925:42"/>
he ſaith to this Aſſertion, <hi>Yea;</hi> did men onely ſay it, it might be queſtioned, and if they ſay otherwiſe now, it is no matter. All men are too prone to lie; but the Holy Spirit is to be firmely believed, becauſe what ever he ſaith is pure and true. Now he in teſtifying of Chriſt in the Goſpel witneſſes nothing but Life to be in Chriſt, and to be the portion of thoſe that believe in him, that the believer in him ſhall not periſh whatever death come upon him, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever trouble; but ſhall have everlaſting life; yea, in a ſort he hath it, for <hi>he that hath the Son hath life,</hi> ſaith the Record which God gives us of his Son, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12. and in teſtifying of ſuch as are righteous men and merciful, taken away and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from among men in ſuch an evil day <hi>when all the Beaſts come to devour,</hi> he ſaith <hi>they enter into peace, and reſt in their beds, each one walking in his uprighteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 56.9. &amp; 57.1.2. that teſtimony the Holy Ghoſt that ſpake in the Prophets (and particularlarly in <hi>Iſaiah, Acts</hi> 28.25) beareth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Demonſtration, Argument and Evidence, evidencing in what they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>viz. That they may reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and their works do follow them.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are two particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34925:42"/>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>that they may Reſt from their Labours.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>And their Works do follow them,</hi> or, <hi>follow with them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Wherein is implied,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note</hi> 1. That they that <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> (and eſpecially from the time of the Beaſts rage, and the great exerciſe of the Saints patience) have Labours and Services, that in the time of their life they are imployed in, indeed <hi>all things are full of Labour, man cannot utter it,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.8. and the Saints have their portion of Labours more eſpecially in or in more eſpecial manner of labours. <hi>There is a man whoſe Labour is in Wiſdom, and in Knowledge, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.21. and in ſuch things the Saints and holy men do labour too, <hi>they labour in the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.58. But here the word <hi>uſed,</hi> ſignifies a toilſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; yea, as ſome note of it, a painful, weariſome, ſpending labour: Yea, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times variety of Tribulations, Calamities, and Croſſes; ſo as ſometimes to threaten Death. And ſo we find the word <hi>Labour</hi> often joyned with Toil, or words of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.19. the <hi>Work and Toil of our hands,</hi> are joyned together, as Work and Labour here; and toyl of the hands may well anſwer to labour here, in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34925:43"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.42. <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaith, <hi>God hath ſeen my affliction and the labour of my hands;</hi> when he ſpeaks of that troubleſome labour, in which the Drought by day conſumed him, and the Froſt by night, and the ſleep de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from his eyes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 40. And the like is uſed of the rigorous and afflictive Service and Labour which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were put to in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when they were made to grone under their Burthens, ſo as their lives were bitter with hard bondage <hi>in morter and brick, and in all manner of ſervice in the field;</hi> when all their Service that they ſerved was with rigour, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.13, 14. with 2.24. Of this <hi>Moſes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs them to ſay, <hi>the Lord looked on our affliction, and on our labour and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> Deut. 26.7. and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.10. it's joyned with ſorrows when it is ſaid of men, <hi>that if by reaſon of ſtrength we attain to fourſcore years, yet then is our strength la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and ſorrow;</hi> where Labour cannot ſo properly ſignifie work and ſervice, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las then men are paſt that; but rather toil, and exerciſe as <hi>Solomon</hi> joyns together, <hi>Labour and vexation of heart,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.22. and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> complains. <hi>Wherefore came I out of the womb to ſee Labour and ſorrow?</hi> Jer 20.18. And that which we read in the Text, <hi>Trouble,</hi> is in the Margin, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34925:43"/>
to the <hi>Hebrew, Labour,</hi> Job 5.7. And ſurely, eſpecially in times of great Perſecution, there is labour and ſorrow more abundantly to exerciſe them, as both in <hi>Jeremiah's,</hi> and the time here ſpoken of. Yea, labour and buſineſs is generally, with exerciſe, grief, and trouble, the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here <hi>of them that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.12. both in reſpect of civil and outward concerns for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; weakneſſes, infirmities, ſickneſs, pain: and in reſpect of the labours, griefs, and travails of the Soul for themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; (temptations alſo from Sathan, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions from men, and much care and exerciſe of ſpirit) that they might obtain the grace and favour of God, with Chriſt and be found in him, and ſerve their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration according to his will. In which ſenſe alſo,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour firſt goes before and then Eating, Reſt or Reward follows after; no injoyment of the bleſſed ſtate of Reſt, but for the labourers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.10. <hi>The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman firſt labouring muſt be partaker of the fruits,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.6. <hi>Six days ſhalt thou labour,</hi> goes before <hi>the ſeventh is the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of the Lord thy God;</hi> the reſt appointed by him, namely, for thee to reſt in, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.9.10. there is Labour that we may be found in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34925:44"/>
Chriſt, or be accepted of him whether pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or abſent, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. and <hi>labour</hi> in the Lord to be performed and undergone 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Through much affliction we muſt enter the Kingdom of God,</hi> Acts 14.22. Service to God, and ſufferings to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone both for and from God; and the will of God in all to be done before we receive the Promiſe, <hi>the recompenſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> Heb. 10.35, 36. yea, and there muſt be faithfulneſs in this too to the Death, elſe no bleſſedneſs; they that endure temptation, and patiently continue in well doing, are the bleſſed that ſhall have Everlaſting life, &amp; receive the crown &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.28, 29, 30. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7. But then it is ſpoken out plainly, that</p>
            <p n="3">3. They that endure and are faithful to the Death (and eſpecially in ſuch ſad times of tryal) ſo as to <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> they are bleſſed in this, that <hi>they Reſt from their Labours</hi> God is a merciful &amp; righteous God, and he hath prepared, <hi>and there remains a reſt for his people,</hi> Heb. 4.9. He that would have a Sabbath or day of reſt for Servants and Cattel now, one in every ſeven days, that they might reſt, <hi>Deut</hi> 5.14. He will certainly give reſt to his wearied, tired, toild People, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants that have laboured and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34925:44"/>
had no reſt here. He calls us to himſelf to give us reſt for our Souls, and to give us reſt too with himſelf from our Labours, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28, 29. and <hi>his reſt is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> Iſa. 11.10 <hi>Reſt from their ſorrow and fear and hard Bondage wherein they were made to ſerve,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 14.3. Reſt with the Apoſtles, when they that are at reſt and eaſe here ſhall be diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>even the Inhabitants of Babylon and the Perſecutors,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.5, 6, 7. with Jer. 50.34. then ſhall they receive their ſad things in tribulation, that now trouble Sion, when the Beaſt-worſhippers <hi>ſhall have no reſt day nor night,</hi> then ſhall Chriſts faithful worſhippers have perfect and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual reſt with Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.11, 13. yea, <hi>they that dye in the Lord</hi> thenceforth ſhall be herein eſpecially <hi>bleſſed,</hi> as their labours and troubles thenceforth are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſharper, their dangers, fears, and griefs more abundant, now they ſhall be eaſed of them all, and by how much their Sufferings were ſharper, and their Labour more toilſome and grievous, by ſo much will their Reſt be more ſweet and welcome, and the greater the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Death in general puts an end to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of this life, as well as to its enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to men whether they be good or bad,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34925:45"/>
as they be properly the exerciſes of this life, though not always as to the kind in general; they that joy in God here ſhall joy much more then, as to their ſpirits; and they that fear and grieve in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences for fear of Hell here; dying in their ſins ſhall much more fear, and feel horrour in their Conſciences then. But as to bodily Pains, and the Fears and Labours of this Life and pertaining thereto, Death puts an end to them, both to good and bad; but yet not ſo to the Wicked as to give them reſt, or make them therein bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they being reſerved by it as in a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon unto far worſe miſeries afterward; and tormented at the preſent with reſtleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fears or horror not having Chriſt to be their reſt: But they that <hi>dye in the Lord</hi> are generally at reſt. And as to be out of and at reſt from greater ſorrows and ſufferings is more deſirable, welcome, and beneficial, then to be out of ſmaller: ſo they that from that time <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> ſhall be in their reſting from their labours more happy and bleſſed then others. But all that <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> in the proper ſenſe before explicated, enter into this reſt: <hi>for they are at home in Gods preſence, and his preſence will give them reſt,</hi> Philip. 1.23. 2 Cor. 5.8. Exod. 33.14. then the Soul
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34925:45"/>
ſhall have <hi>reſt in its Husbands houſe,</hi> as was prayed for, for <hi>Ruth, Ruth</hi> 2.9. then the Body reſts in the duſt from its Pains Weakneſſes, and Afflictions, and Labours <hi>Job</hi> 3.13, 17. &amp; 17.16. and the ſpirit en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters more fully into peace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.2. and it is ſaid to theſe Souls, <hi>That they muſt reſt a little while till the time of their Brethrens ſufferings alſo be accompliſhed,</hi> Rev. 6.11. Yea the whole man, though parted aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Soul from Body, <hi>reſts in ſafety not hearing any more the voice of the oppreſſour,</hi> nor aſſaulted by the tempter, <hi>Job</hi> 3.18. &amp; 11.18. <hi>the ſmall and the great reſt there, and the Servant is free from his Maſter,</hi> Job 3.19. Yea, the end of the Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Affliction they have here, is, that they may reſt then from it <hi>till the pit be digged for the ungodly,</hi> Pſal. 94.12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They reſt from their Labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And their works follow them,</hi> or, <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Works</hi> are ſomething diſtinct from their <hi>Labours;</hi> their Labours had Pain, Sorrow, and ſoil, like to <hi>the Labour of a Woman in Travail, that hath ſorrow becauſe her hour is come,</hi> Joh. 16 21. and their toil and pain proceeds partly from their own infirmity, partly from <hi>the bondage to corruption</hi> under which the whole Creation
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34925:46"/>
grones, <hi>the Curſe upon the Earth,</hi> Gen. 5.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 20, 21, 22, 23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2, 4. partly from the Badneſs, Wickedneſs, and Oppreſſiveneſs of the World, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of Sathan, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. But their works are as the fruits of thoſe Labours, the Man-child brought forth as it were, the things done by them in the body, the fruits or <hi>works meet for repentance,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.10. Philip. 1.22. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.8. with <hi>Acts</hi> 26.20. and theſe they have (with all their ſtrength and courage to endure the labour attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them) from Jeſus Chriſt, that root of <hi>David,</hi> in whom they are ingraffed, root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and grow, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.16. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7. He is the <hi>green Fir-tree from whom all their fruits are found,</hi> Hoſ. 14.8. the true Vine of whom they are Branches, and from whom (they abiding in him and his Word in them) they derived ſuch ſap and juice, vertue and ſpirit as made them bring forth much good fruit, ſo as the Father (the good Husbandman) is therein glorified, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.1, 4, 5, 8. being and truſting in him, and making him their hope, they were <hi>like trees planted by the waters ſide, bringing forth their fruit in ſeaſon,</hi> Jer. 15, 7, 8. though we are juſtified by Faith without the works of the Law, yet we are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34925:46"/>
too by Works and not by Faith only, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.24. not by a Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, but by <hi>a Faith that worketh by Love,</hi> Gal. 5.6. the believing, in which we receive the forgiveneſs of ſins and are juſtified to life, is not a bare ſpeculation of, or aſſent to, the Opinion or Doctrine of Truth reſting in the brain; nor ſo far one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affecting the Heart as to eaſe it of, and quiet it from, its griefs and fears; but it is ſuch a believing as is to the <hi>ſaving of the Soul,</hi> Heb. 10.39. even to the ſaving it from the power of ſin and Sathan, as well as in other reſpects. Such a perſwaſion of the truth of Gods teſtimony, and ſo that Jeſus is the Son of God and Saviour of the World, and that all that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles have delivered concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and the grace in and by him is true; as wherein the heart is ſo affected with him, and drawn to him, as that it ſaith of him, <hi>He is my rock, and my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs, my God in whom I will truſt:</hi> So as it comes to him for all direction and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, Grace and bleſſing, and yield up it ſelf to him, to obey and follow him in a confident expectation therein of meeting with his promiſed Salvation and Bleſſing. And where with the heart a man ſo belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it is to righteouſneſs, and will not be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34925:47"/>
barren &amp; deſtitute of the fruits of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or of the works of righteouſneſs, piety, charity, &amp; all goodneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91 2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.35, 37. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9, 10 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>And theſe works, in Death and when dead follow them, or follow with them, ſo as they ſhall be rewarded of God, for God is not unrighteous to forget their work and labour of love, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labour nor work ſhall be forgotten, their labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord who tells their wandrings, puts their tears in his Bottle, and keeps account of them in his Book, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8. and <hi>their work ſhall be rewarded,</hi> Jer. 31.16. And that</p>
            <p n="1">1. In ſome ſort at the time of thier de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence, and in their ſeparated ſtate, in that they have in their Conſciences the joy and comfort of their Works, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurance of further reward in the day of the glorious Appearance of the Lord Jeſus; their works are now eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God and laid up in his treaſures: laid up, as it were, with them, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with them to be brought forth to open view in the day of Chriſts glorious appearing. And the Reward is alſo laid up, reſerved and unalterably appointed for them; as was before noted from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34925:47"/>
ſo that they not onely have hope in their Death, but alſo after their Death there is a Separation of them from others according to their Works; ſo as that whereas others are caſt into Priſon; and reſerved, as it were, in Chains of Darkneſs againſt the Judgment of the great Day, the wicked is reſerved to the day of Deſtruction, and they ſhall be brought forth to the day of Wrath, when <hi>the Heavens ſhall reveal his iniquity, and the Earth ſhall riſe up againſt him, and his way ſhall be declared to his face and he ſhall be repayed what he hath done.</hi> Job 21.30, 31. &amp; 20.27. theſe that dye in the Lord are at reſt and ſafe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver quiet from the fear of evil, being out of the reach henceforth of Sathan and all his inſtruments, and whatſoever may trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or diſquiet them; they that can kill the Body, and it may be have killed theirs, have no more now that they can do to them, their ſorrow and ſighing is for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver paſt; and they are comforted in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe and in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome while others are tormented, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. for they are in Paradiſe with Chriſt, as Chriſt ſaid to the Malefactor that confeſſed him, <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe,</hi> Luke 23 43 Their Soul or Spirit dies not (as ſome hold) with the Body, but returns to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34925:48"/>
God, into whoſe hands they commit it, as they pray him to receive it, ſo he doth receive it too, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.5. &amp; 49 15. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23. Yea, they may be underſtood to be thoſe that ſtand with the Lamb upon mount Sion, and that ſing the new ſong with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody of Harps unto God, which no man elſe can learn, they being in a more full and proper ſenſe <hi>redeemed from the Earth and from among men</hi> then any yet here living, and as to thoſe that ſuffer and <hi>dye in the Lord from henceforth;</hi> from the time of <hi>the Beasts rage</hi> when there will be the moſt remarkable time of the Saints patience, at the time (probably) when <hi>the Beaſt that aſcends out of the bottomleſs Pit</hi> ſlays the Witneſſes which is his laſt act, his part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blow, the ending part of his Rage, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.7. (which Chapter takes in all the time from the firſt to the laſt) that ſinging with Harps may denote their ſpecial trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Bleſſedneſs; which agrees with what is ſaid in <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. where there is the ſame number of the Sealed; and where it is ſaid, that <hi>they that came out of great</hi> (or as the words may be rendered the great) <hi>tribulation were arayed in white robes, having waſhed their robes and made them white in the blood of the Lamb;</hi> where the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34925:48"/>
white Robes doubtleſs are emblems of ſome Great Prieſtly or Kingly dignity, as is implied in <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.4.5. ſuch as is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.10. &amp; 20.6. and as is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in what follows, when it is ſaid, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they before the Throne of God night and day in his Temple</hi> (as the <hi>Beaſt-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers are tormented and have no reſt day nor night,</hi> Chap. 18.11) <hi>and he that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the Throne dwelleth among them, they ſhall hunger no more, nor thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sun light on them, or any heat; for the Lamb who is in the midſt of them ſhall feed them, and ſhall lead them to the Fountains of living waters, and God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes,</hi> Chap. 7.13, 17. Let me add this upon this quotation that it may appear that thoſe Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend men that appointed that ſeventh Chapter or part of it, to be read on the day dedicated to the Memory of <hi>All Saints,</hi> ſurely underſtood thoſe things to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable to the Deceaſed Saints that <hi>dyed in the Lord:</hi> But yet their great and proper reward is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Fully at the day of the Appearing again of the Lord Jeſus, at that day the Crown of Righteouſneſs <hi>henceforth</hi> from the time of Departure laid up, ſhall be given to all
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34925:49"/>
that love and look for that his Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>The Son of man</hi> our <hi>Lord Jeſus ſhall then when he comes in the glory of his Father with all his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, reward every man according to his works,</hi> Matth. 16 27. Rev. 22.12. and then their Reward ſhall be great and glorious indeed, and gloriouſly manifeſted; for then <hi>them that ſleep in him will God bring with him, the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.14, 16. not in mortal bodies to labour and travail again, <hi>but their mortal then ſhall put on immortality, and their corruptible ſhall put on incorruption, and what was ſown in diſhonour ſhall riſe in glory, and what in weakneſs ſhall riſe in power:</hi> and <hi>what was ſown a natural body ſhall riſe a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al body, faſhioned into the likeneſs of Chriſts glorious body,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.43, 44, 53. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. <hi>and then they ſhall have no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying nor pain, for all thoſe former things ſhall be wholly paſt,</hi> Rev. 21.4. no nor ſhall they have any thing of errour, ignorance, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, nor of fear or grief in their mind, or inward man, but they ſhall then know as they are known, <hi>and ſee face to face, and be made like to Chriſt ſeeing him as he is.</hi> 1 Cor. 13.9, 12. 1 Joh. 3.2. <hi>Then they ſhall appear in glory with Chriſt,</hi> Col. 3.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34925:49"/>
3, 4. <hi>having fellowſhip with him, and him ever amongst and with them, and God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and with him,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.9. 2 Theſ. 2.14 &amp; 1 Theſ. 4.16. Rev. 21.3. injoying <hi>the new Heavens and the new Earth wherei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dwells righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.14. and the <hi>new Jeruſalems glory which comes down from out of heaven,</hi> having the glory of God and her light like to a ſtone moſt precious, like a Jaſper ſtone clear as Chryſtal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10, 11. eating and drinking with Chriſt at his Table in his Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. injoying the incorruptible Inheritance that is undefiled and fadeth not away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 4. and the <hi>incorruptible Crown of Life, Righteouſneſs and Glory which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them that love him,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.25. 2 Tim. 4.8. James 1.12. <hi>even the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and glory of God and of Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhall have the fulneſs of joy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for evermore at his right hand;</hi> and <hi>ſee his face and have his Name in their foreheads, and have an everlaſting</hi> happy <hi>day without any night the Lord himſelf and the Lamb being their everlaſting Light, and they ſhall reign for ever and ever,</hi> Matth. 25.35. Dan. 7.27. 1 Pet. 5.10 Pſal. 16.11. &amp; 36.8, 9, 10. Iſa. 60.19, 20. Rev. 22.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>Which thing I onely here mention, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34925:50"/>
more particularly ſpoken ſomething to them in my Book called <hi>Balaam's wiſh.</hi> O Happy, happy, and thrice happy porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that be ſo dead!</p>
            <p>So much for the Explication and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words. Let us now Apply it briefly.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p n="1">1. ANd firſt, it tends wonderfully to commend and magnifie the Lord Jeſus to us, who makes thoſe that are in him even ſo happy in Death; He being the Root and well-ſpring of all the Happineſs and Bleſſedneſs injoyed, or injoyable by the Saints and holy ones either in this Life or in and after Death; or at and after the Reſurrection of the Dead: Well may we then joyn our aſſent to that Song of or in the kingdom, that Song of the Elders (mentioned by our Deceaſed Siſter on her Death-bed) and ſay, [<hi>Thou art worthy to open the Book, and unlooſe the Seals of it; for thou waſt ſlain and haſt Redeemed us to God by thy Blood,</hi> &amp;c] as alſo to that of the Angels that follows, <hi>Worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain to receive
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34925:50"/>
power, and riches, and wiſdome and ſtrength and honour, and glory, and bleſſing,</hi> Rev. 5.9, 12. magnifying alſo the Riches of the love and grace of God, even the Father in appointing and giving him forth to us, and ſo filling him through Death and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, with all his own unſpeakable ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he might be the Authour of ſuch Bleſſedneſs to us; and ſo we may alſo joyn our aſſent to that of every Creature in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and under the Earth, and ſuch as are in the Sea, and all that is in them, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſing, Honour, Glory and Power be to him that ſitteth upon the Throne and to the Lamb for ever and ever,</hi> Rev. 5.13. and to that of the innumerable number out of all Nations, Kindreds, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Tongues ſtanding before the Throne, and before the Lamb, clothed with white Robes, and having Palms in their hands, <hi>viz. Salvation to our God which ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the Throne, and to the Lamb,</hi> Chap. 7.9.10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To commend and ſet forth the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and deſireableneſs of the ſtate of thoſe that are in Chriſt Jeſus and abide in him, that they however deſpiſed and abuſed of men, are the happieſt men in the world, their portion better than any other mens, <hi>the Heritage of Jacob</hi> to be preferred before
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34925:51"/>
all the enjoyments of the great Princes of the Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.14. So as it may well be ſaid, the righteous (they that are in Chriſt Jeſus, walking not after the Fleſh but after the Spirit) are <hi>more excellent then their neighbours,</hi> Prov. 12.26. however Poor, Meane, Illiterate, Afflicted and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the Righteous be; And however Rich, Learned, Honoured, or otherwiſe adorned and qualified their neighbours, that be not righteous, are. Yea, well it may be ſaid, <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael, a People ſaved by the Lord the ſhield of their help, and ſword of their Excellency; thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall be found lyars to thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon</hi> (as deſpiſing) <hi>their high place,</hi> Deut. 33.29. <hi>O Lord of hoſts: bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the man that putteth his truſt in thee,</hi> Pſal. 84.12: Bleſſed at all times, bleſſed in Life, more bleſſed in Death, but moſt bleſſed in and after the Reſurrection of the Dead.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To commend Piety and Godlineſs, and the exerciſe thereof to us, which hath the Promiſe of all this great bleſſedneſs, both of the life that now is, and that that is to come, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. &amp; 6.6.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To condemn the blind judgment and practice of the world, that ſleight, hate, and perſecute theſe things, accounting thoſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34925:51"/>
that are and that dye in Chriſt (eſpecially in a way of perſecution) to be unhappy and their portion deſpicable; which things I onely mention: But beſides</p>
               <p n="5">5. It directs us whither to flee for ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and refuge againſt the fears, and feelings, horrours, and harms of Death the King of Terrours, namely to Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, who hath both aboliſhed or deſtroyed its deſtructive power by his Death, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed him that had the power of it, the Devil,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.10. Heb. 2.14. and alſo hath the keys of Hell and Death, Power, and full Authority over it, and over the dead, <hi>having dyed, roſe and revived that he might be Lord both of the dead and of the living,</hi> Rom. 14.19. as he hath that ſharp Sickle in his hand, ſo he can cut off with it high or low, rich or poor; and he can keep it off or back during his pleaſure, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtate of it, and the perſons in it as ſeems good in his ſight. And in him there is deliverance from the horrour and harms of it; as he is the forgiver of the ſins, both that occaſioned it, and that might render it as an inlet into a worſer ſtate then it ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of it ſelf containeth, and hath both Authority (and proclaims himſelf ready graciouſly to do it) even both to raiſe out of it, and in the interim to ſecure from <pb n="92" facs="tcp:34925:52"/>
harm and miſchiefs by it; yea, and to make it greatly uſeful and advantagious to us, to make the day of it better then the day wherein we were born, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. a Chamber of eaſe, reſt and ſafety to us from the evils either fore-afflicting us, or further threatening, and abiding the yet dwellers on the Earth, or abiders in the land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. &amp; 57.2. an outlet to our cares, fears, labours and temptations to ſin, or toils by ſuch temptations; and an inlet, ſafe Port, or entrance into peace, and ſecurity the end of our exile and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and beginning of our actual admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in our ſpirits into our Fathers preſence, and glorious fruition of our bleſſed Saviour that wonderful one, the unparall'd lover of our Souls; and Paragon and Pattern of all divine and heavenly vertue and excellency; the Lamb that had mercy on us, and dyed, roſe again and lives for ever for us, the Lord Jeſus. He is that Sun that ſhining into our hearts the light of the knowledge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and of the glory of God in him; and being believingly beheld by us, will drive out and expel all that darkneſs of our ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errour that in the night of our unbelief obſcures our minds and fills us with frightful fears of Death and its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents, and chaſes away all thoſe miſts
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34925:52"/>
and vapours ariſing out of the muddineſ, of our hearts, to the ſadding us at the thoughts of its approches; and by his warming influences (as ſtreaming forth by his Holy Spirit in the Goſpel the beams of his love and favour in the forgiveneſs of our ſins, and intereſting us in his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and precious promiſes of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and everlaſting Life and Happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſs, and ſo the lively hope of his Salvation and Glory to be injoyed by us) he can and will ſo chear and comfort us, as to make the grim viſage of Death amiable to us, and the paſſage through it very deſirable. <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23. yea and give us hope and joy in Death, as the beſt hour that ever came upon us. And he is that (and ſuch a) ſhield too, that encompaſſing us about with his favour and defence, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing himſelf between us and our enemies, even Death and all its train and power, ſecures us againſt their fierceſt aſſaults and ſharpeſt darts, being <hi>the Death of Death, the Deſtruction of the Grave and Hell,</hi> Hoſ. 13.14. we being in him, and incompaſſed about with his arms of love, nothing ſhall be able to approch us to hurt or harm us. He is ſuch a Fountain of living waters that whoſoever drinks of him (receiving his Doctrine into his heart, and retaining and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34925:53"/>
keeping it there) ſhall not die of thirſt; Such a Heavenly Medicine (being Gods Salvation or ſaving health) that whoſoever takes him down and taſtes the ſweetneſs of his Love, and Grace, and keeps it, or the reliſh of it upon his palace, ſhall not taſte Death, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. &amp; 8.51, 52. Yea, thoſe Waters he gives, and the Medicine he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords, will ſpring up and effect in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver and taker down thereof, Life in Death, even Eternal Life. The Tree of Life that was in the firſt Paradiſe, and which being eaten of, would have preſerved the life of Man for ever is loſt, and there is no recovering it again, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.22, 23, 24. Nor can all the Phyſicians in the world find out or compoſe a Medicine that can keep us from Dying. But our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his heavenly Wiſdome and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is that Tree of Life in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God; that Sovereign An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote of Gods own finding out, making, and propounding, which being eaten and taken down, will ſecure us againſt all the Poiſon of the old Serpent; the evil of this natural Death, and carry us ſafely through it, and bring us certainly out of it to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality and eternal Life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2, 3, 14. He will both make the Soul live and be happy in Death and raiſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34925:53"/>
up the Body to an immortal ſtate of bliſs, <hi>Iſa</hi> 55.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.25, 26. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p>In vain do men weary themſelves and ſpend their Eſtates to find out a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſtone that may turn all things into Gold. Here is that true <hi>Elixir</hi> that will turn all to Good; and as <hi>he hath recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled all things in himſelf that are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that are in Earth,</hi> Col. 1.20. ſo will he reconcile all things to us, and make them ours and for us, deſtroying that in all things, and all thoſe things and perſons that are inflexibly againſt us. Thence the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them that are his called according to purpoſe,</hi> Rom. 8.28. <hi>and all things are yours</hi> (for your uſe, ſervice or benefit) <hi>whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or World, or Life, or Death, or things preſent, or things to come, all are yours, and you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> 1 Cor. 3.21, 22, 23. Death is in the Believers Inventory as a parcel of his Goods, as one of his Servants or Friends; yea, and all things too that ſhall follow after it: <hi>For all the ways or paths of the Lord are mercy and truth to them that keep his teſtimonies and his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> Pſal. 25.10. <hi>There ſhall no evil
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34925:54"/>
happen to the juſt,</hi> Prov. 12.21. <hi>He that keepeth the Commandments ſhall feel no evil thing.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.5. O infinitely precious Jewel and Pearl of great price, <hi>the Bread which came down from heaven, which whoſo eats of, ſhall live for ever,</hi> Joh. 6.50, 51.</p>
               <p>But yet the being of this Refuge doth not of it ſelf ſimply ſecure us againſt the hurts of Death, they that neglect it ſhall periſh without eſcape, however good, ſafe, and ſure a Defence it is, and affords. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. Death will do them this hurt (as we have forenoted) that it will ſhut them out from all ways and paſſages to the after-life; it will cut off all further opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſeeking for ſafety in, or injoying ſafety by or from this refuge. This Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote will not preſerve from fears or harms of Death, unleſs both taken and kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our hearts. This <hi>Elixir</hi> will not turn all to gold or good, unleſs injoyed by us or duly applyed. This Sun will not ſhine on us to expel our darkneſs, and refreſh and chear us, unleſs we be and walk in the light and virtue of it; nor this Shield de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and ſecure us againſt Deaths harmful darts, no nor from (what is indeed the Dreadful thing) the ſecond Death, unleſs it be about us, and we, as it were, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its compaſs; no, nor will any thing or
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34925:54"/>
perſon elſe do it beſides him: For God the Father is in him, and not to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched to, or his favour injoyed, but in and by him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.6, 7. Nor is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit but upon him, or any other ways to be injoyed, then by turning at his Reproofs to believe in and obey him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.15, 16, 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.32. <hi>neither is there Salvation in any other Name beſide,</hi> his that was Crucified for us and Dyed for our ſins, and Roſe again for our juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, <hi>under heaven, whereby we may be ſaved.</hi> Acts 4.11.12. The Law and its deeds cannot juſtifie and ſave us; for by it is the <hi>knowledge,</hi> not the forgiveneſs of ſins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Riches profit not in the day of wrath,</hi> it is onely <hi>righteouſneſs delivers from death,</hi> Prov. 11.4. nor will our works or righteouſneſs that are not of the Faith of him profit us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.12. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.8, 9. <hi>for they that are of the works of the Law are alſo under the curſe,</hi> Gal. 3.10, 11, 12. and works of our own deviſing are of no worth with God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15, 9.10. Nay, <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> cannot ſave us, becauſe not Crucified for us; nor have they that Name into which we may be Baptized for the Remiſſion of our ſins and receipt of the Holy Ghoſt, to renew and regenerate us, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34925:55"/>
not any other man. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, 13. the wiſe Virgins Oyl will not relieve the fooliſh Virgins that have none of their own, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.8, 9. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his,</hi> not another mans <hi>faith, Hab.</hi> 2.4. and therefore there is (as we have alſo ſhewed before) an abſolure neceſſity of our being in Chriſt, that we may have this bleſſedneſs by him in and after Death. Unleſs we be in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>He is</hi> not <hi>made to us of God,</hi> as to our enjoyment thereof, <hi>wiſdom, righteouſneſs, ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and redemption.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30. The Ark ſaved none from periſhing by the Flood, but thoſe that were in it; nor will Chriſt ſave from the ſecond Death or, give bleſſing in this to any out of him, <hi>He that hath not the Son hath not Life,</hi> though that Life be given us in him that it might in receiving him be received with him. 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.11, 12. The Feaſt, though prepared and invited to, ſatisfied not its refuſers; but they were excluded and cut off from all they had beſide, for refuſing it, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.4, 7. yea, and being come into, he muſt be abide in too, ſo as to Death and in Death, elſe we yet periſh. He that draws back, Gods Soul will have no pleaſure in him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. A Caſtle though never ſo ſtrong will
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34925:55"/>
not ſecure from the potent and vigilant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, him that either comes not into it, or after he hath been in it, upon any terms forſakes it. And this is uſeful further,</p>
               <p n="6">6. To invite and provoke us all with all earneſtneſs and diligence to betake our ſelves to Chriſt this refuge, and being in him, to abide in him; to live and dye in him, and by no means neglect or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him. <hi>Enter into this rock and hide our ſelves in the duſt of the earth, even in the duſt of his Death, for fear of the Lord, and for the glory of his majeſty,</hi> Iſa. 2.10. Pſal. 22.14. Death will come upon us ſooner or later, that cannot be avoided, nothing more certain; yea, it may come ſuddenly upon the youngeſt and ſtrongeſt of us; for nothing more uncertain then the time of its coming, <hi>for ſurely every man in his beſt ſtate is altogether vanity,</hi> Pſal. 39.5. and though of it ſelf it will not hurt us, nor ſhall we periſh in it, but be raiſed up again from thence: Yet our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining our ſins, and refuſing or neglecting to be waſhed and renewed, and ſo to be partakers of Gods Salvation, that will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to, and pull upon as a ſecond Death; yea, and this Death will put an end to all poſſibility of eſcaping that, and be an entrance into that dreadful Priſon,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34925:56"/>
in which the Debter and Malefactor will be kept ſafe till the great Aſſiſes, and then the Execution of the Eternal Judgment will ſucceed. Now is the accepted time; now the time of eſcape, and this the way to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape; to be found in Chriſt. O then how doth it behove and concern every man to look about him, and give diligence with the Apoſtle, to win Chriſt, and be found in him, not having our own righteouſneſs, but that which is by the Faith of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But may ſome ſay, Can we make our ſelves in Christ? can we enter into him as we will? can any come to Chriſt except the Father that ſent him, draw him? Is it not of God that any man is in Chriſt Jeſus and not of himſelf? why then do you call upon us to this, as if in our power?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We do not ſuppoſe that any man can of himſelf come to, or make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in Chriſt Jeſus. Nor do we call upon any to do ſo of himſelf; they that make Salvation and Damnation the moſt abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters of meer Deſtiny; doe not they alſo (yea who more) call upon men to get into Chriſt; labour to be found in Chriſt; And yet they tell men, that onely
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34925:56"/>
a certain number that muſt come and be irreſiſtably brought into him, can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly come into him. Others (ſay ſome of them) are as much neceſſitated to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh through the defects of Gods actings, or his non-actings, as thoſe that muſt come are neceſſitated to live through his effects; witneſs Dr. <hi>K.</hi> anſwer to Mr. <hi>Goodwin.</hi> Theſe indeed are harſh Taskmaſters like <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that required the tale of Brick, but gave them not materials neceſſary for their performance; Nay, worſe then he, for there was Straw to be had for their ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it and gathering it; onely they had not time enough to do that and fulfil their tale of Brick too. But theſe tell them there is no ſufficient Grace for them; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the grace in Chriſt is not ſufficient, but becauſe it is not for them. So another known Authour that I forbear to name, and yet theſe ſay too, men muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for not coming to Chriſt and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him.</p>
               <p>But to the Objection I ſay, Both that the way into Chriſt is open for all (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 100.1, 4.) and that it is the work of God to make a man in Chriſt, and it is a work he is ready and deſirous to work; and to that purpoſe he calls men to Chriſt in and by his voice in his Goſpel, in and with
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34925:57"/>
which he is both preventing men with grace bringing Salvation, and is <hi>drawing them and taking off the yoke from their jaws, and laying meat before them,</hi> that they might come to him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11. and in their yielding up to him he works there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in them, and brings them into him, and makes them in him <hi>Doth not wiſdome cry! doth not underſtanding put forth her voice,</hi> Prov. 8.1. Can that be denyed? and to whom? <hi>ſhe cryeth without, and utters her voice in the ſtreets, ſhe crieth in the chief places of concourſes, in the opening of the gates, coming in at the doors, and in the city ſhe uttereth her voice, Turn ye at my reproofs,</hi> Prov. 1.20, 21, 22, 23. &amp; 8, 2, 3. <hi>To you, O men</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>I call, and my voice is to the ſons of men,</hi> indefinitely; <hi>yea, to the ſimple, and thoſe that have no understanding,</hi> verſ. 4. and Chap. 94. ſhe bids <hi>Look to me and be ye ſaved all the ends of the earth,</hi> Iſa. 45.22. <hi>The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, the Lord calls and hath called the earth from the riſing of the Sun to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the ſame,</hi> Pſal. 50.1. And what ſaith Wiſdom, or the Lord by her, <hi>O ye ſimple, understand wiſdom, and ye fools be ye of an underſtanding heart,</hi> Prov. 8.5. She ſaith not, Make your ſelves wiſe and underſtanding, but as one onely able
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34925:57"/>
and furniſhed for doing it, ſhe bids them onely be made ſo by her, and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Hear and receive her inſtruction, <hi>&amp;c. verſ.</hi> 6.10, 32, 33. as elſewhere, <hi>Be ye converted.</hi> Acts 3.21. <hi>Be ye reconciled,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.20. and divers the like. And by her Voice and Inſtruction (which is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Gods Voice and Inſtruction, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is drawing men to Chriſt, <hi>and every one that</hi> hears and learns of the Father cometh unto him) <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44, 45. there he is putting forth his hand, and that not an empty or idle hand, but operative and graciouſly bountiful, as knowing our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and poverty, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.2. and thence calls to us to give our hands to him; yield our ſelves to, and comply with him, by the help of his hand to enter into his Sanctuary and ſerve him; as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſaid, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.8. comparing the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal (which is after the Hebrew) read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Text. And thence the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet complains, <hi>There is none that ſtirreth up himſelf to take hold of thee,</hi> Iſa. 64.7. as implying Gods nighneſs and preventing us with ſtrength; but mans lazineſs and ſtubbornneſs in refuſing to uſe the Talent given, or put forth the ſtrength afforded, putting his hand into his boſom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to pull it out, and give or yield it to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34925:58"/>
in complyance with the Lord. The ſame nighneſs of God to us and his graciouſneſs is implyed in our Saviours ſaying, <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the door and knock, If any man hear my voice and open to me, I will come in to him,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 3.20. And in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles exhorting not to <hi>receive the grace of God in vain, becauſe he ſaith, in an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted time have I heard thee, in the day of ſalvation I have ſuccoured thee, now is the accepted time, now is the day of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> 2 Cor. 6.1, 2. thence God faults mens wills, <hi>Ye will not come to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that ye might have life.</hi> Joh. 5.40. and <hi>Why will ye dye.</hi> Ezek. 33.11. and <hi>I would have gathered, but ye would not,</hi> Matth. 23.37. Now which ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, God, or man? God lays fault on mans will, for their wilfulneſs when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents them, and is at hand to help them, that they might come to Chriſt; and men, too many, lay the fault on Gods will, and ſay in effect, God will not, and meerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not give them grace that they might; the Lord puts the fault in men, and ſaith their deſtruction is of themſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 23.9. and men put the fault in God, and ſay in effect, their deſtruction is of him, as it is ſaid, <hi>The fooliſhneſs of a man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts his way, and then his heart frets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34925:58"/>
the Lord,</hi> Prov. 19.3. <hi>The ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful man ſaith, There is a Lion in the way, I ſhall be ſlain in the ſtreets,</hi> Prov. 22.13. not becauſe there is much danger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but as an excuſe for his ſloth, he ingages his heart to ſome corrupt intereſt, and then ſaith for excuſe, I <hi>have married a wife, I cannot come.</hi> Luk. 14.20. It is true the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>It is not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth; but of God that ſheweth mercy,</hi> Rom 9.16. and the ſame have I ſaid in this that I have here ſaid; but he ſaith not, it is not <hi>to</hi> him that willeth, nor <hi>to</hi> him that runneth in the ſtrength and incouragement given of God in his mercy; for that would croſs what our Saviour in effect ſaith in <hi>Matth.</hi> 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 7, 8. when he ſaith, <hi>Ask and ye ſhall receive, ſeek and ye ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened to you: for every one that asketh receiveth, and he that ſeeketh findeth, and to him that knocketh it ſhall be opened.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Enq.</hi> But what ſhall or muſt I do then that God may bring me into Chriſt, and make him to me, Wiſdom, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:34925:59"/>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Comply with his Calls and Counſels turning at his Reproofs. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. &amp; 4.10. <hi>Hear, and thy ſoul ſhall live.</hi> Iſa. 55.3. <hi>He bids repent and believe</hi> the Goſpel. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.15. And I ſay ſo too, repent of theſe vain excuſes and put them away, repent of minding other things and neglecting the Goſpel, and Gods ſalvation therein, that God having given Chriſt for thee and holding him forth to thee; and Chriſt having giving himſelf for thee (for it was <hi>for all men.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6.) and made peace and atonement through his Blood, and being filled with all the fulneſs of God, and calling thee by his Goſpel, and ſtanding ready upon thy compliance to help and ſave thee, to pardon thee and give thee his holy Spirit, admit thee into his favour and protection, and make an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant with thee; yet thou let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt him ſtand without knocking, and doſt not take him into thee, nor yield thy hand to him to be taken in to him, but runneſt away from God thy Saviour after lying va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; after the World, and the Fleſh, and the Devil; after pride and Covetouſneſs, and the like; laboureſt for the bread that periſheth, and refuſeſt to ſeek and labour in liſtening to, and following thy Saviour, for that bread that endureth to everlaſting
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34925:59"/>
life that he would give thee. Repent of this thy carriage, and ſo alſo of ſeeking Gods favour by any works or ways of thine own or other mens propoſing, and not by and in liſtening to him. Repent of theſe and all other like things, and believe and obey the Goſpel. But be ſure it be the Goſpel thou believeſt, not what any (though an Angel) ſaith contrary to or beſide the Goſpel. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6, 9. Not thoſe doctrines of men, That God hath rejected the moſt men abſolutely before they were born, and is not willing they ſhould be ſaved, contrary to 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. that Chriſt Dyed not for all, but only an Elect number, contrary to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2, 2. and the like do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and ſo all ſuch as deny the Perſon, Satisfaction, Reſurrection or Mediation of Chriſt, his Perſonal appearance, the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, the laſt Judgment, and the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repent, and believe the Goſpel. If thou ſayeſt, How canſt thou believe? Is not Faith the gift of God?</hi> I anſwer. Yes; and he gives it in a ſober and diligent hearing of his Word, not wilfully cloſing the eye and ſtopping the ear, and hardening the heart againſt him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thine ear then and hearken unto him,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34925:60"/>
                  <hi>Hear and thy ſoul ſhall live.</hi> Iſa. 55.3. yea, <hi>while it is ſaid,</hi> (or called) <hi>to day, if thou wilt hear his voice, harden not thy heart,</hi> and thou ſhalt hear and live, onely obey in hearing as he enables thee and is in the power of his light and truth by his Spirit working in thee to will and to do of good pleaſure. Work thou out in his <hi>working thine own ſalvation with fear and trembling,</hi> Philip. 2.12, 13. <hi>doing all things without murmuring or disputing.</hi> verſ. 14. putting away and not wilfully retaining what he reproves, and yielding thy ſelf to God to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his counſels and inſtructions; waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him is his wayes, and looking to him and calling upon him as he enables thee for his help; and thou ſhalt be ſaved. Be but willing to this, <hi>Conſent and Obey;</hi> and though thou haſt been, or hitherto art as bad as one of the Rulers of <hi>Sodom,</hi> or as the people of <hi>Gomorrha, thou ſhalt eat the fruit of the land,</hi> the promiſed land. <hi>Thy ſcarlet ſins ſhall be white like ſnow, and thy crimſon ſins like wooll,</hi> Iſa. 1.10, 18, 19. Be but as induſtrious in minding and following after the Goſpel and after God and Chriſt as drawing, inſtructing, and ſtrengthening thee, as thou haſt been, and others are for the World, and for their corrupt deſires and luſts, and thou mayeſt lay hold on
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34925:60"/>
Eternal life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.1, 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11, 12. This is the ſum of the inſtructions given by the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> when having affirmed that every good gift, and every perfect giving, comes from above, from the Father of Lights with whom there is no variableneſs or ſhadow of turning, and that of his own will begat he them by the word of truth, that they might be a kind of firſt-fruits of his creatures. He adds and infers, <hi>Wherefore, my beloved Brethren, let every man be ſwift to hear, ſlow to speak, ſlow to wrath, and laying apart all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, receive with meekneſs the ingraffed word which is able to ſave our ſouls; but be ye doers of the word and not hearers onely,</hi> James 1.17, 18, 21, 22.</p>
               <p>But then it is to be minded too, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving begun to doe thus, it in necceſary to go on and to continue in ſo doing; abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Chriſt, minding and believing the Goſpel, and obeying it and him in and by it; and exerciſing our ſelves to believe on him, and following after him that we may know him more and more, and ſo be more rooted and grounded in and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him, walking in him according to our receipt of him, and taking heed of what might turn us out of the way of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. As of</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:34925:61"/>1. <hi>High-mindedneſs,</hi> as if we were rich enough, and knew and had attained enough already. <hi>Prov</hi> 16.18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Sloth,</hi> and what principles tend to that, and to high mindedneſs, Such as That, that if we have once believed aright we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, whatever we may do, totally and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally miſcarry, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Taking offence at either Gods ways and providences, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2, 3, 12, 13, 14. Or at thoſe that fear God, ſo as to break Communion with them, leſt forſaking the Aſſemblies and ſitting alone we grow hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, and for want of right exhortation and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to cleave to God, withdraw from him through an evil heart of unbelief. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12, 13. &amp; 10, 24, 26, 29. or elſe we fall into the ſnares of ſuch as would ſeduce us: againſt which things the minding and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in Gods Law will ſecure us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.165. and hereto alſo it's good and needful to pluck out the right eye where it offends and caſt it from us; for in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and unity with the fearers of God, God doth command his bleſſing and life for evermore, <hi>Pſal</hi> 133.13.4. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.9.10, 11. Take heed too</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:34925:61"/>4. <hi>Of the Love of the World and of the things in the world,</hi> and of whatſoever do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or practice may <hi>corrupt us from the ſimplicity</hi> in and ſingle cleaving to Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15, 18. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, 3. I enlarge not to theſe things, nor add any other leſt I be volumnious.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whereas we may be tempted to grow Weary, by reaſon of the many Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Troubles, Temptations, and Toilſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Fleſh that we may meet with in the way of God and of godlineſs, and eſpecially in times and caſes of Perſecutions; here it alſo incouragement to patience, not only becauſe Chriſt hath faithfully promiſed to be with his followers in their ſufferings and ſervices to help them, as is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.10, 13, 14 and that in the taking courage and not cowardly deſponding and laying down our reſolutions and endeavours to walk with God, but waiting upon him, he will ſtrengthen our hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.14. &amp; 31.24. Yea, and is faithful and will not ſuffer us to be tempted above what we are able, but will with the temptation give an iſſue that we may be able to bear it. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. but alſo from this here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed after the mention of the patience and conſtancy of the Saints in faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>viz.</hi> The Bleſſed ſtate of the dead
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34925:62"/>
that dye in the Lord, that they then reſt from their Labours, and ſhall receive a good Reward, <hi>Hold we fast therefore the profeſſion of the Faith without wavering; knowing</hi> that we ſhall have ſuch a Reſt and Recompence; and <hi>that we have need of patience, that after we have done the will of God we may receive the Promiſe And yet a little while and He that ſhall come will come and will not tarry.</hi> Heb. 10.23, 35, 36, 37. let us not for want of a little longer hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our way, and induring Affliction, looſe ſo ſweet a Reſt and ſo wondrous a Bleſſedneſs as is in Chriſt Jeſus ſet before us. Remember we, and be warned by <hi>Sauls</hi> example, who for want of a little more patience, an hour or two longer tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying for <hi>Samuel,</hi> loſt his Kingdom, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10 8. &amp; 13.8, 9, 10, 12, 13. Behold we and learn of <hi>the Husbandman, who waiteth for the precious fruits of the earth and hath long patience for it until be receive the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and the latter rain;</hi> and <hi>be we alſo patient</hi> in ſeeking and waiting for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Heaven: ſtabliſh we our hearts, <hi>for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh,</hi> James 5.7, 8. O that our eye may be ſo upon the bleſſed and glorious Reſt to be injoyed by us at Night, as that we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the heat, and burthen of the Day, or
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34925:62"/>
of that little ſmall part of it that yet remains</p>
               <p n="8">8. And then here is a motive and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement too, to diligence in the work and ſervice of the Lord, and an Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to take heed of loytering and idleneſs, or of doing badly; becauſe our works fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us. Our Wealth will not follow us, nor any Places or Dignities, mens Honours ſhall not deſcend with them, onely their Works that they may be diſpoſed of, and in the great day receive Rewards ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according thereunto; let us then give diligence in good works to the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of hope to the end, and not be ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but followers of thoſe who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes, ſeeing <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget any work or labour of love ſhewed unto his Name.</hi> Heb 6.9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>The ſleep of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring man is ſweet whether he eat little or much.</hi> Eccleſ. 5.12. let us labour and be induſtrious in the work of the Lord and then whether we have much or little in this world, we ſhall have a ſweet comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſt and ſleep when we go out of it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; for he will ſo ſatiate the weary Soul, and repleniſh every ſorrowful Soul, as that when it awakes it ſhall be able to ſay with <hi>Jeremiah, My ſleep was ſweet
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34925:63"/>
unto me,</hi> Jer. 31.25, 26. to this end let us look diligently to our Lord Jeſus, cleave cloſely to him, and abide in the believing views and remembrance of him, who as <hi>He gave himſelf for us that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem us from all iniquity, and purifie to himſelf a peculiar people zealous of good works.</hi> Tit. 2.14. ſo he alſo is the <hi>root</hi> from whence we may derive all grace and virtue, to make us fruitful, <hi>Rev</hi> 22.16. Avoid we the counſel of the ungodly, the way of ſinners, and the ſeat of the ſcornes, and exerciſe, our ſelves diligently day and night in the Law of the Lord, the Goſpel of our Salvation, that ſo we may be as the Trees of the Lord full of Sap, even filled with the fruits of Righteouſneſs that are by him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2, 3. &amp; 104.16. Be we <hi>always ſtedfaſt, unmovable,</hi> from the hope of the Goſpel and ways of Righteouſneſs, <hi>abounding in the work of the Lord, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we know that our labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord,</hi> our works ſhall follow us to be gloriouſly rewarded by him, when we ſhall Reſt from the pain, labour and exerciſe attending them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Laſtly, it affords Comfort alſo to us in behalf of ſuch as <hi>Dye in the Lord,</hi> that we may not immoderately Mourn for them
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:34925:63"/>
as thoſe that have no hope. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16, 17. Death takes them not away ſo as they periſh from their Hope, they ſhall Riſe again, yea, God will bring them with Chriſt, and they ſhall Riſe Firſt, as is there ſaid; in the mean time they are at Reſt, and their good works are not loſt, but follow with them and they are Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>Comfort we our ſelves, and one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with theſe words, yea, Comfort we our ſelves in behalf of this our Siſter deceaſed, with them, whoſe Deceaſe occaſioned (as She alſo before it requeſted it) our Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of theſe words.</p>
               <p>Truely though ſhe had here Weakneſſes and Infirmities common to humane fallen nature, and was not without all ſuch defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as ſpring from Paſſions, and leſſer ſins, for which God was pleaſed alſo to chaſten her for ours, and others admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet we may through the grace of God afforded to and received by her, not doubt to ſay, That ſhe was a good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and God humbling her by his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and chaſtiſements did her much good in the latter end, and ſhe ſhewed good proof of her profiting thereby, her heart being much taken with, and ſet for the knowledge of God and Chriſt in his Goſpel,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34925:64"/>
as we might in ſome good meaſure perceive in that ſhe was very attentive to it, and deſirous to have her Children (though but Mother in-law to them) mindful thereof alſo, walking ſoberly and harmleſly; as alſo in both her former Lying-in, when ſhe had a very weak time (ſo as there was little hope of recovery for a great while) ſhe gave very good proof and evidence of her Faith and Patience, ſo as to ſing in her very great Weakneſs to God and his praiſes. And in this laſt Lying-in, whereof ſhe dyed (as in all her languiſhings and great weakneſſes before it) ſhe behaved herſelf with ſo good hope in God, and deſires of being diſſolved and being with him; and with divers ſuch Chriſtian and gracious ſpeeches and demeanours, as gives us good hope comfortably to judge her one of thoſe Dead that have <hi>dyed in the Lord;</hi> and therefore to be Bleſſed, as being at Reſt from all her Labours, Weakneſſes, Languiſhings and whatever Toyls, Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles or Temptations ſhe here encountred with, and that what good fruits are Works ſhe brought forth and acted, (as ſhe was not without ſuch) follow with her into Gods preſence, ſo as that, through Chriſt and his Blood waſhing both her and them, ſhe ſhall receive for them a good Reward
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34925:64"/>
in the Kingdom and Inheritance to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
               <p>Bleſs we God, That there is ſuch a way made for us to be made good, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain through Chriſt ſo good hope for our ſelves and others, that we may live and dye in the Lord and be ever Bleſſed: And Bleſs we him for the good wrought in her and the good hope ſhe expreſſed in Chriſt and God, and that we have concerning her: And let it be our great care ſo to believe on and abide in Chriſt, that we li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in and unto him while we are here, may alſo Dye in him and injoy the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing here pronounced by this Voice from Heaven that ſaid, <hi>Write, Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord from henceforth. Yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed be God.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:65"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34925:65"/>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <head>Epitaphium in Amicam ſuam D<hi rend="sup">am.</hi> 
                  <hi>REBECCAM JACKLER.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IMbecille fuit corpus, quod terra repoſtum</l>
                  <l>Jam tenet in gremio non temeranda ſuo.</l>
                  <l>Mens fuit &amp; variis curis obnoxia, quare</l>
                  <l>Hoſpitio fragili feſſa domum petiit;</l>
                  <l>Quam proprio noſtrum miſereſcens ſanguine Chriſtus</l>
                  <l>Omnibus aptavit, conſtituitq bonis. </l>
                  <l>Et nunc quam foelix! cui nec jam corpus onuſtum</l>
                  <l>Morbis, nec curis mens agitata ſuis.</l>
                  <l>Mens etenim athereas per Chriſtum aſcenſa cathedras</l>
                  <l>Omnibus impetibus libera tuta manet.</l>
                  <l>Gaudia percipiens ibi talia, qualia nullus,</l>
                  <l>Quantumcunque ſciens, hic habitans capiat.</l>
                  <l>Queis &amp; ei everſo Chriſto veniente ſepulchro</l>
                  <l>Aeterno ſocius foedere corpus erit.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:34925:66"/>
               <head>An Epitaph Upon his Deceaſed Friend Mrs. <hi>R. J.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WEak was the Body which within its womb</l>
                  <l>The conſecrated ground doth now intomb.</l>
                  <l>Her mind expos'd to cares, lothing at laſt</l>
                  <l>So bad a lodging to that Home made haſt,</l>
                  <l>Which Chriſt through his own Blood of grace prepared</l>
                  <l>And gives to all good men as their reward.</l>
                  <l>And now how well in mind and body ſhe</l>
                  <l>This from Diſeaſes, That from cares being free!</l>
                  <l>Her mind the heavenly Seats through Chriſt her guide</l>
                  <l>Aſcended, free from paſſions doth abide.</l>
                  <l>Such joys injoying, as none here below</l>
                  <l>However knowing, perfectly can know.</l>
                  <l>Wherein when Chriſt hath quite or'e-turn'd the Grave</l>
                  <l>It ſhall its Body partner ever have.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
